<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Questions of profitable and pleasant concernings talked of by two olde seniors, the one an ancient retired gentleman, the other a midling or new vpstart frankeling, vnder an oake in Kenelworth Parke, where they were met by an accident to defend the partching heate of a hoate day, in grasse or buck-hunting time called by the reporter the display of vaine life, together with a panacea or suppling plaister to cure if it were possible, the principall diseases wherewith this present time is especially vexed.</title>
            <author>O. B., fl. 1594.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120718</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855912</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855912</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00410)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 375:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Questions of profitable and pleasant concernings talked of by two olde seniors, the one an ancient retired gentleman, the other a midling or new vpstart frankeling, vnder an oake in Kenelworth Parke, where they were met by an accident to defend the partching heate of a hoate day, in grasse or buck-hunting time called by the reporter the display of vaine life, together with a panacea or suppling plaister to cure if it were possible, the principall diseases wherewith this present time is especially vexed.</title>
                  <author>O. B., fl. 1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 34, [5] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field, dwelling in the Blackfriers by Ludgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: O.B.</note>
                  <note>A dialogue.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The display of vaine life.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dialogues, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21420:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21420:1"/>
            <p>QVESTIONS OF PROFITABLE AND PLEASANT CONCERNINGS, TAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of by two olde Seniors, the one an ancient retired Gentleman, the other a midling or new vpſtart frankeling, vnder an Oake in Kenelworth Parke, where they were met by an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to defend the partching heate of a hoate day, in graſſe or Buck-hunting time called by the reporter the <hi>Diſplay of vaine life,</hi> together with a <hi>Panacea</hi> or ſuppling plaiſter to cure if it were poſſible, the principall diſeaſes wherewith this preſent time is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vexed.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Field</figDesc>
               <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Richard Field, dwelling in the Blackfriers by Ludgate. 1594.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21420:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21420:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE ROBERT DEVORAX, EARLE OF ESSEX AND Ewe, Vicount of Hereford, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Borchier and Louaine, Maiſter of the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties horſe, Knight of the noble order of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and one of her Maieſties honorable priuie Counſell. Your honors moſt bounden <hi>O. B.</hi> wiſheth long and happy life, with encreaſe of honours.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight honorable, hauing found this booke of profitable concernings and pleaſant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, collected by the diligence of ſome one, who it ſhould ſeeme ouer heard the matters, at ſuch times as they were talked vnder an Oake in the parke at Kenelworth, ſome few yeares paſt: I thought it my dutie, meeting with the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof, to dedicate them vnto ſuch a principall worthy as your honors ſelfe, who haue alwaies hitherto bin found floriſhing and budding forth to all vertues, in ſuch forward ſort, ſo as the world hath conceiued an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted hope, you will alwaies hold greene and laſting in the increaſe of them, without ſuffering any rottenneſſe or corruption of vices at any time to approach you. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the principall ſubiect of matter herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſetteth out the notableneſſe of ſuch former wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, as haue through the perfection of vertues abſolute in themſelues, deliuered ſucceſſiuely the fulneſſe thereof <pb facs="tcp:21420:3"/> ouer vnto their poſteritie, it could not but meane your worthy ſelfe, eſpecially when I called to minde the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of your honorable father deceaſed, who in his life time ataining to the tipe of vertues worthily acquired, through the full &amp; entire poſſeſſion of them, was no doubt in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſufficiently able to deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer as peculiar &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per bleſſings to his worthy ofſpring, ſo that now they are found no leſſe excellent &amp; effectuall vertues in your ſelfe &amp; the reſt of his ſucceding children, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were in his antecedent ſelfe. Withall I moſt humbly beſeech your honour, not to thinke I preſume hereby to adde any forces to your ſtrong vertues, which are already ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently knowne and magnified, euen of them that are beſt able and moſt worthy to iudge: but rather being priuie to my owne vnworthineſſes, onely deſire to ſhew, that there neither is, nor hereafter ſhall be, any abilitie to do dutie hidden in me, which for lack of diligence I would leaue vnperformed: Neither go I about to thinke that it is poſſible for me to expreſſe that which belongeth to the due deſert of your incomparable vertues. A matter alſo ſuperfluous for me to do, conſidering that euen as the ſhadow followeth the body, ſo glory and renowme aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciateth the excellent parts of noble and well deſeruing men. The principall thing right honourable that I had herein to regard, was that the matter might fall out fit and beſeeming the dignitie of your worthy ſelfe, whom I haue bin bold to chooſe as patron to preſent the argument of this booke vnto: wherin I confeſſe I haue not ſo tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly obſerued my charge neither, but haue wittingly faulted therein alſo, foreknowing as I do, that your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor can ſpare no houres from the vtilitie of common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths matters, to beſtow ſo much as one looke vpon the vnworthineſſe hereof. Yet for their ſakes, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
<pb facs="tcp:21420:3"/> if they will, may reape benefit hereby, I haue made bold to hope your honor will vouchſafe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it, wherein you may according to the words of the Goſpell hauing enough your ſelfe, receaue at my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy hands that alſo, whereof you haue no neede. If your honor for their ſakes vouchſafe to agniſe my duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full endeuoures, it will prooue ſuch a ſufficient reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing vnto me, as ſhall binde me for your ſo great fauour and pardon, dayly to pray for your honours encreaſe and growth vp to all the happineſſes your heart can wiſh. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching almightie God further, that as mightie <hi>Gedeon</hi> receiued ſtrength and furniſhings, of all neceſſary aids and meanes to preuaile and ouercome his enemies the
<hi>Madi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites,</hi> at the time of his faithfull ſeruing and calling vpon God vnder an Oake in <hi>Ephah.</hi> Euen ſo vnder the ſeruice and command of our gracious and neuer fading greene Oake, planted and watered by the hand of God, to be the ſhelter of vs all vnder her fauourable aids, your honor, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſuch other worthies, tried and approoued partakers in all aduentures, may bring vnder the enemies to God and our Chriſtian peace: ſo that in the end alſo, God bleſſing your labours, you may build vp an altar of peace for the behoofe of this land, as <hi>Gedeon</hi> did vnder his Oake, which he called <hi>Iehouah Salom,</hi> the God of peace.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours honours moſt bounden, O. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21420:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ithence the world is become ſo ſtomack-fallen to abhorre all meates, I haue thought good to commend vnto the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, this <hi>Panacea</hi> or ſupl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>g plaiſter, to cure if it were poſſible all diſeaſes. The drench you may imagine to be made by the <hi>Pithagorians Academickes, Peripateticks, Epicure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and the reſt, wherein if the curious vaine of euery appetite be not fitted, yet the aſſay and taſte thereof cannot hurt, becauſe the entire and whole thing which ſhould haue brought loathſomneſſe with it, is not at all offered here. The Authors of this medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, fearing that if they ſhould haue filled vp their ſpeeches with copious words, to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſatiſfying, through it mellow ripeneſſe, it would haue died at the firſt reuealing, as many other more worthy and better approoued things haue done. Auoiding alſo by continuall proceſſe all tediouſneſſe, thorough which they ſhould haue bin comberſome to themſelues, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in like manner others with an entire thing, haue therfore taken the way, brieflie to cut off all copious ſpeaking, leaſt the matter ſhould haue proceeded more infinitely, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either their leaſure or the matter required: contenting one another with the bare ſence of things, on purpoſe to continue life in the matter, knowing it notwithſtanding to be ſubiect to withering as all other things are. Abhorring beſides, as it ſhould ſeeme to argue any thing to a triall through painted guile or ſupportation of Arte. Now howſoeuer the matter frameth, I may hope not to purchaſe the grudge or enuie of any, medling not at all therein farther then may beſeeme the vprightneſſe of a reporter: yet therein alſo as becommeth me, intreate the readers eſpecially Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and the better ſort, in whom there is alwaies to be found huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and moderation, not to enterpret things to the worſt, but rather to pardon falts which all men are ſubiect vnto: to whom I commit the correction of my ſelfe, ſo far as I haue offended, if they may pleaſe to vouchſafe the paines, knowing that they will at the leaſt allow me as great a libertie to confeſſe my owne ignorance, as to iuſtifie other mens knowledges. Now for the enuious and ignorant, I deſire to haue it taken of them as a tale told to deafe men, but to the wiſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, I hope it may prooue a ſong ſung in a wood, that had a profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table eccho. For whoſe ſakes alſo I had thought to haue compaſſed out this matter with another meate wand, but that the multitude of precepts ſhould haue bin thereby obſcured, a fault and hinderance to haue made open and plaine things leſſe knowne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:21420:4"/>
            <head>THE DISPLAY OF FOLLIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="day">
               <p>
                  <hi>Huddle.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ee you neighbour <hi>Dunſtable</hi> what hote ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring there is made after the Buck ouer yonder land? were it with you and me as it hath bene ſince each knew other, we could not behold ſuch ſport thus farre of, but rather ſo farre as might become vs, keep way with the formoſt. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> Sir then was then, and now is now, they that cannot do as they haue done, muſt content themſelues with what they may do: pleaſeth it you therefore to giue ouer the game in the plaine fielde, and to let me tie vp our horſes to yonder bough, repoſing our ſelues awhile vnder the ſhade of this goodly greene Oake. <hi>Hud.</hi> I readily conſent to your indifferent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Becauſe it is vnwholſome and not altogether ſafe to ſleepe in this wilde wood, let me beſeech you to diſcourſe ſuch matters as our experience may delight vs to remember: withall, voutchſafe I pray you, to report the newes of London, for thence I vnſterſtand your maiſterſhip is lately come. <hi>Hud.</hi> With a glad will, but ere we enter into them, let me firſt tell you what I lateſt heard, which proouing true will equally glad vs both. This noble Earle is not come hither to take an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable recreation only, as heretofore he was wont, but purpoſeth withall to keepe a ſtanding houſe here the whole yeare tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> But that I feare the contrarie, how ſhould I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at theſe glad tidings. <hi>Hud.</hi> My ſelfe in like manner hold the matter doubtfull, knowing the ſpeciall imploiments her Maieſtie hath daily to make of his moſt approoued good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices being ſtill as he hath bene alwaies ſo excellent a becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſtates peare, that his worthineſſe cannot but carrie him from vs to matters of farre greater conſequence. To ſay truly, <pb facs="tcp:21420:5"/> our vntoward deſeruings haue merited no ſuch benefit from him for longer then we are receiuing good turnes at his hands, or in hope of his pleaſuring vs, no longer can we ſtay our tongs from curſing, banning, and vngracious deprauing his noteable parts, whereof we are moſt vnworthy to iudge, yet alwaies take vpon vs ſingular skill and knowledge: were it therefore but our vngratitude onely, then which hell hath not a more vgly vice, it alone were ſufficient to diſcourage ſuch hopes of our good as from the rich treaſure of his honourable bounty other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might likely deſcend vnto vs. Our malignant hearts are bent towards this Gentleman like as the double deuoted Iewes were againſt our Sauiour Chriſt, whom they worſhipped and reuerenced ſo farre, as miracles and their owne gaine might ſtir them vp to admire him, further they would not haue to do with him, vntill the time came they were able to betray, lay vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, or crucifie him. Now this good Earle, his Chimneyes ſmoake, to prepare wherewithall to cram and fat vp our ſwine bellies, now we wonder at him, and terme him noble Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, honourable Lord, wiſe counſailer, and the princelieſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect any realme Chriſtened hath or had in our memorie. Falſe harted hirelings ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſay thus while Beefe &amp; Breweſſe laſteth then, with falſe black breath, boiling from out a venemous ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack blaſt the ſweete bloſſoms of his frutefull vertues, which euen now had almoſt bin made profitable vnto vs, had we not put foorth our ſnakiſh toungs tipt with the poiſonfull hiſſing of ſlander and detraction. But now I long to heare the faults you haue obſerued in my long ſpeech, hoping you will deale plainely in manifeſting them vnto me.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> Since it is your pleaſure to ſtay your diſcourſe with a deſire to heare my plaine eloquence, I rather blame you for ſpeaking too little againſt that which is ſo worthy reproofe, then otherwiſe thinke much or that you ouer ſaid in the Earle his praiſe. To ſay truly, ſuch are our groſſe manners, not caring what we ſay ſo we ſay ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, and ſomwhat we muſt ſay, elſe could not the world take knowledge of our ſufficiencies, which ſerue vs much better to finde wants in other men, where they are not, then to feele the burthen of our owne extremities, lying heauy vpon our ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21420:5"/> ready to breake our weake backs. For my part, I meane to turne that curſed ſpeaking you named into hartie praier, that it may pleaſe God to further this noble man his purpoſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, both to this whole countries benefit, and alſo to the enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging of other noble and worſhipfull Gentlemen, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie him in loue and good will, to do the like by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, where they dwell. A thing ſo much diſcontinued and ſo farre worne out of faſhion, that vnleſſe by ſome notable man it be reduced and ſet vp againe, the old ancient patterns loſt and gone, I feare me, it will hardly or neuer catch the right ſhape a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, men haue ſwarued ſo much to the new cut, wearing all on London faſhion, where they neuer thinke on their poore countries, ſaue on quarter rent daies only. <hi>Hud.</hi> Though you ſpared me on the maine which ſtood in your way, you thought to nick me on the bye, not ſet for you. The ouerſight I made in comparing the Iewes dealings with God and Chriſtians their behauiour towards man, that miſtaking you would not ſee, though too apparant to a curious eye: but free and tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things to be vſed or laide aſide, according to the occaſions and diſcretions of men, thoſe you launched at euen out of your reach, preſuming for that you ſhadowed your ſelfe vnder the couerture of a formall figure, finding fault with your ſelfe to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape vndiſcouered, marching with your coulours flying: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you vſe me as the blinde Spaniard his boy ſerued his maiſter, who to make a lurching fault himſelfe, was content not to find his maiſters little digreſſion from the law himſelfe had made, as if a little breache in the one not found fault with, ſhould giue the other a libertie to offend at large. The outſide of your coate neuer gaue me cauſe to ſuſpect any ſuch lining: beſides, what your ancient patterns and faſhions ſhould meane, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily geſſe. My yeares being ſome few more then yours, me thinks I ſhould remember from as long a time as you. The while I haue hued, things haue bin gained and bettered by wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer skill and ſufficienter knowledges, whereby to raiſe more profitable and conuenient vſes out of things, as may appeare in matters almoſt of euery ſort. Heretofore had men attained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any little ſmattering or ſmall maiſterie in arts or vnderſtandings <pb facs="tcp:21420:6"/> aboue the reſt, they ſtraight thought it a point of their deepeſt skill to hold others back from the reache thereof, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to haue the more ignorant to dote vpon them, elſe could not the maiſters of balductum ceremonies, haue climed vp by craftie conueiance, to ſit in thrones aboue Emperours and Kings. I ſuppoſe by your ancient patterns and faſhions, you meane apparell and hoſpitalitie, wherein to my ſmall power I will do my good will to take away the error of your miſlike, beginning firſt at apparell. Amongſt ſundry ſorts of men there haue alwaies bene diuers kinds of attires, according to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors degrees &amp; abilities of the wearers, the ſhape &amp; faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euer in the or dainers choiſes to pleaſe themſelues according to the deuice and conceit of beſt becomming. Therin this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age hath rather ſurpaſſed, to their commendation, fitting nearer by Tailers ſhapes and garniſhings, with better propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning and ſetting out garments, to their bodies, then the Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terking Tailors of the old ſtampe, wherevnto you would haue faſhions brought back againe. You might as well appoint men to go naked or looſely attired, which they haue done, as not to allow them that muſt were clothes, to fit their bodies according to their owne minde and fantaſie. Had you found fault with too coſtly apparrell, where neither the degree nor place requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it, or with too fantaſticall or ſuperfluous wearing, where halfe the ſtuffe would ſuffice to make a farre more ſeemly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or had you ſpoken againſt their follies, who fet enuious patterns to outvie and vndoe one the other, by trying maiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in faſhions, who ſhould bcare the prodigall bell away: which time and coſt had bin better ſpent in the emulation of vertues acts, who ſhould haue deſerued beſt in deeds of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall proweſſe beſeeming fortitude: therein had I agreed with you: but through the haſt you made to finde out theſe, not ſo worthie your diſpleaſure, ſuch haue alſo eſcaped you. I rather thinke you wanted words to expreſſe your good conceit, not accuſtomed to ſpeake in ſuch things, then any wayes come ſhort of iudgement to diſcerne aright in greater difficulties. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Surely you fauour me rightly; for it was my meaning to ſhew the diſlike I had of ſuch as weare more on their backs in <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21420:6"/> one day, then their fathers did in their whole life time. <hi>Hud.</hi> Now I dare vndertake by your waightie words, you meane ſuch as weare more armour on their backs in one day, or are girte with more wounds and ſtripes then their Fathers were.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> Nay rather, I ſpeake againſt that exceſſe, where commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Farmes which were wont to maintain &amp; bring vp honeſt tennants and their children, ouer and aboue the rent, are daſht vpon one ſute of apparrell together with one daies vnmeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble expences.
<hi>Hud.</hi> I perceiue you could be content to dwell rent-free, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grudge you beare hereat, all the daies of your life. But now to your patterns of houſekeeping, I will ſee to fit you better therein, for I know that troubles you moſt, and giueth you leaſt cauſe of offence. Know you how all fathers that leaue their heires lands, charge the ſaid liuings? Firſt the mother her carrying away a iointer, moueables and furniture of the houſe, that muſt needs be one hinderance why the ſonne ſhould not begin where the father left: then paying out of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and ſiſters portions, is alſo a hinderance to make him leſſe able to keepe houſe and porte equall with your ancient pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne. Now againe, beſides lands and goods, perhaps he wants the offices and entertainmets from his prince, which his father was aſſiſted by, in that ample manner to do that you ſo haſtely require. But put the caſe all Noblemen and Gentlemen were in better ſort able to maintaine houſekeeping after this faſhion, then any anceſtour they had, I will ſhew you ſufficient reaſons, and thoſe profitable alſo to the common wealth, to haue ſuch lauiſh houſekeeping forborne. When you had theſe prodigall ſpendings, for cuſtome ſake, they neither knew why nor wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, a progenie of voluntarie or rather wilfull beggers were thence outrraiſed, the ſwarme and rable whereof by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance haue defamed and ſlandered the whole nation, beſides the generall and particular hurts they do in the places where they are yet in that ſort maintained. Iſ one Gentleman be able to ſhew you halfe a thouſand thus bred and continued, from one deſcent to another, for many hundreds of yeares, it is like Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land hath ſome greater ſtore of theſe ſtraw companions. It were much for me to ſay, that the firſt brawle of them came from <pb facs="tcp:21420:7"/> this occaſion: becauſe of the likelyhood, I will venture to thinke they did and ſhew you my reaſons: Firſt their breeding and cuſtomarie aboade in one place, excerciſing one ſelfe kind of life; then the commodiouſneſſe of a waſtefull houſe, to fcſter them vp in that free and liberall ſort, without exception to any that would helpe away with beefe and mutton, as much at their commaundement, that would in this ſort come to take it, as at theirs whoſe breeding and growing it was of. For it is more likely they tooke their beginning from houſes thus wantonly kept, then from a farther fetcht deuiſe of Abbeys and Priories, whoſe benefacting that way extended chieflie to their ſuppoſed children and Paramoures, inhabiting Milles and out-granges within their belles ringing, whither by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaps they made their Sabaoth dayes iourneys: their cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing was onely of ſuch, to do to haue, as the Scot ſaith, an eaſe for a pleaſure. Againe, ſuch as were fallen by caſualties or bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome occaſions of many children into pouertie, former times, I muſt confeſſe, had greater reſpect in time to ſee to them then we haue, who lightly alwaies by charitable contributions reſtored the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> back againe, &amp; in time, to an eſtate ere they could catch a habit or delight therein: a matter better pleaſing no doubt to the parties relieued, then the other contemptuous cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of wilſull begging. Now whether it be likely that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurale houſe keepings were the occaſions to draw loyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring diſpoſed perſons from labour to eaſe, and from one enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing degree to another, till it had fully poſſeſt them to erect a habit or facultie of ſlouthfull beggers: the firſt degreebeing in themſelues through this prouiſion, other members of their like ſort and qualitie, as the rogue and vagrant begger, in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed haue proceeded from the number and ſuperfluitie of the firſt kinde: now I ſay the better conſideration hereof to iudge, I referre to your ſelfe. <hi>Dun.</hi> Through your gentle teachings, I begin to perceaue an approoued error, in ouerdoing, as well in things that haue good purpoſes and intents, as alſo in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters grounded vppon miſchiefs, carrying an outward ſhew of holy and religious deeds. I confeſſe, Monaſteries and Priories were not ſo likely to haue bin cauſes hereof, as the other diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21420:7"/> houſes, where refreſhings were without reſpect or partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. The Moncks and Abbots of my knowledge, cut large ſhiuers of the loafe for which they neuer ſweate, to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſtrong in the peoples fauour and opinion, or elſe ſpent their whole gettings vpon vnlawfull children. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding by your fauour, you haue not attained vnto the full of my meaning and deſire herein. <hi>Hud.</hi> I confeſſe I haue not, for the fight of beefed beggers that thronged ſo thick in my way: but now I haue got paſt them, I will go neare to meet you on your owne bawlke. Your deſire is to haue houſes kept to beare the Lord of miſrule company at Chriſtmas, ſpending then vpon Hick and Stephan, who haue no need of it, what would maintaine a ſeemly family more then halfe a yeare. Such may well be called the Lord of miſrule his gueſts, who beſides exceſſiue ouer-eating &amp; drinking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, ſpoiling by miſuſe that they cannot deuour, leaue behind them alſo ſuch vnman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly annoyances, called beaſtialities, that the Nobleman and Gentleman that hath thus crammed his quoiſtrels, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie forſake their houſe and houſekeeping, till a good winde blow away the vnpleaſant ſauours their Chriſtmaſſe Poulcats leaue behind them. Thus beſides exceſſiue coſt and trouble by the fruits of this careleſſe hoſpitalitie, their houſes are leſt in worſe caſe then common Innes or oſtelries. If it be a ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhearing feaſt, maiſter Baily can entertaine you with his bill of reckonings to his Maiſter, or three ſheapheards wages, ſpent on freſh cates, beſides ſpices and Saffron pottage. So that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman &amp; Gentleman ſhould haue nothing come in clearly to them at any ſeaſon, if your ancient patterns might be rightly obſerued. I know your meaning is not to haue the Hockedame waited on by them, who for the moſt part let their lands to halfes, or elſe conuert all into rent. The entertainment one of them giues vnto another cannot be that you call ſo hotly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for thoſe faſhions you haue a homely terme I liſt not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you of. <hi>Dun.</hi> The money your maiſterſhip hath ſpent in learning and trauell, is euery penny better beſtowed then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Now I plainly ſee, let an ignorant man be neuer ſo wiſe, or of neuer ſo great experience, but if he meete with a man of <pb facs="tcp:21420:8"/> gifts and bringing vp, his preſuming to know all things proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth plaine ignorance, and meere miſtaking. Once to day I tooke my ſelfe to know as many wayes to the Church as mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Vicar himſelfe, but now I ſee Plowmen are no preachers. I haue a Sonne that hath coſt me many a quarter of corne, on whome for this dayes worke I will beſtowe one Peck of pure graine, which toucht no chaffe this many a day, to buie him more learning; and though I am not able to breed a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, I may perhaps, as well as ſome of my neighbors, bring vp one.
<hi>Hud.</hi> I meruaile how you ſtumble on the Church and the Miniſter: this hote weather and our long talke ſhould rather haue put you in minde of the Butler and the Butterie. Beſides I cannot bethinke me what vertue ſhould be in your peck of pelfe, eſpecially to alter nature; my ſelfe withall the proofe I could make, could neuer finde the skill to cauſe a barking mongrell to become a true queſting Spaniel. To be plaine with you, I neuer thinke an Ape more diformed, then when he ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by borrowed skill, to put on that which nature cannot grace: nay rather thoſe things are moſt vgly, which are forced and done in ſpight of nature. Euery one to whome Maſterſhip belongethis not a Gentleman, what purchaſe ſoeuer his father maketh, vnleſſe he can procure bloud to alter kinde: that you cannot giue your ſonne, becauſe you haue not attained vnto it your ſelfe. The notabilitie hereof proceeds from chiualrie and marſhall proweſſe, where for princes right, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales ſaftie, through worthy aduentures of bloud and life, purchaſe is made at the deareſt price and rate. Therefore as there cannot be a greater cauſe amongſt men, then the Prince and commonwealths buſineſſe, nor a greater matter then bloud and life, to be powred out and parted withall, of neceſſitie the greateſt and principalleſt reſpect and regard hath euer bene had therevnto.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> By your fauour ſir, there are no ſuch lawes yet made to prooue Souldiers Gentlemen: or if there be, it is left out of their ſtile in all that I can reade or vnderſtand of their profeſſion. <hi>Hud.</hi> If you ſpeake ignorantly, I am conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to helpe you ouer the ſtile; you ſeeme not able to clime, but if you play the Foxe with me, grapes are no meate for you, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21420:8"/> eſpecially of my reaching vnto you. Becauſe I haue ſome doubt of your words, and no cauſe to miſtruſt your ſelfe, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my minde herein more ſully. You know how all that are put to learning prooue not learned, neither all degrees of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of like eſtimation: no more are any to be counted Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, vnleſſe they were ſo before their degrees taken in Artes. Likewiſe, all that follow the warres proue not Souldiers, nor all that proue Souldiers, take not their degrees at armes: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe that take degrees, all of one account or worth. For as there are diuerſe kinds of vertues to make vertuous, ſo are there diuerſe degrees of the vertuous, according to the ſorts of the vertues they haue attained The moſt rich and excellent vertues were principally acquired and gotten by princely deſeruing men, the renowne of whoſe glorious deeds hath rightly gotten vnto themſelues iuſt preheminence to guide and go before the reſt, as hereafter I will plainly ſhew you. In their power and Maieſtie onely therefore it is to nobilitate, commend vnto honor, and to make Gentlemen, and not in your peck of droſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ointment, though made of the Quinteſſence of old Angels. Gentlemen bred in the warres, and thoſe that come of them, you ſee are not made, for it is no proper ſpeech, to ſay that is made, which is bred; neither can art or reaſon helpe to make it good. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Without offending you with my rude an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, let me aske you this mannerly queſtion. Do you meane thoſe that are begotten and borne in a Campe, to be onely Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of bloud, or how otherwiſe I beſeech you to ſhew me? I haue heard this matter often debated, but neuer fully agreed vpon. <hi>Hud.</hi> Becauſe you haue alreadie heard it doubtfully handled, and at no time diſcuſt, it may in like ſort become me to giue place to ſome doctor of the Ciuill law, to whoſe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it eſpecially appertaineth to know the certaintie of all worthie antiquities. <hi>Dun.</hi> It fits me not to importune you, otherwiſe I ſhould receiue a great good turne at your maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips hands thereby, for my ſonne takes great delight in pete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Gentlemen, and hath ſome skill in quartering their coates. God willing he ſhall one day waight vpon you to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his knowledges, if it may pleaſe you to accept of his vnworthinesse. <pb facs="tcp:21420:9"/> 
                  <hi>Hud.</hi> Bring him with you on Sonday next to dinner, where you ſhall be ſure of a Pigge for your ſonne his welcome, therein I meane to proue his skill, how he can head and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame; the iawes and eares he ſhall beſtow vpon you after he hath quartered them. The head ſo ſpoiled, he ſhall charge his quadrate trencher with.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> I thought I ſhould make you merry with my miſtakings, I now and then catch a word or two from my ſonne, which for lack of due placing, marreth all in the making. <hi>Hud.</hi> You ſhall in earneſt (if you liſt to carry it with you) heare what I can do in your ſonne his Art. The Pigs head ſhall be vpon a Spit couchant, the toung pendant, the braines dormant in the ſauce poinant. Now for a ſupporter or creſt, becauſe of the quadrufoile in his bare head, there ſhall be a recompence made by purchaſe of the back ribbes and chine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone. All theſe thus put together, muſt of neceſſitie conclude ſomwhat, eſpecially in a morning faſting. <hi>Dun.</hi> Moſt of theſe termes my ſonne hath by heart, and will talke them to a glaſſe window I haue, when many times it is my fortune to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heare him. According to your ſaying alſo he hath often confeſt vnto me, that his wit and memorie haue ſerued him beſt to thoſe purpoſes in a morning eare he haue eaten any thing. But ſtill I am to put you in minde of my former deſire, wherein I am perſwaded you are able to ſatiſfie a much better man then my ſelfe. <hi>Hud.</hi> Rather then to giue cauſe to hinder our exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of ſpeaking, I will do my beſt to content your minde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, hoping you will not put my ignorance vpon me as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, neither returne a bolt weakly ſhot, ſtrongly vpon my ownehead. It ſhould ſeeme there were ignorant times wherein men liued in full plentie ſo aboundant, that they needed not at all to ſearch out or care for, more then the vſe of neceſſaries al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie in their owne poſſeſſions. In progreſſe of further time, while they were thus lulled in their ſoft delights, their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie prouiſion through their numbers increaſing, began as it were to abate and growe emptie, well towards a want on the ſodaine: now the way to ſupply the ſame, was not ſo ready as the neceſſitie grew vrgent; wherevpon ſome few, or rather one aboue the reſt, ſtirred vp by a more ready motion, and better <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21420:9"/> reſolued ſpirit, put forth himſelfe with purpoſe rather to ſeeke remedies where they might likely or poſſibly be found, then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely to ſtay themſelues vpon deceaueable meanes. Theſe few thus quickning their dull ſences, by the inſtigation of that quahtie which is euer leaſt ſubiect to baſe neglect, to preuent that which was like to enſue, they ranged into the world like companions and fellow aduenturers in the behalfe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and the reſt; whoſe cogitations for want of ſtabilitie of courage, could neither reſpect nor take in hand, any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſlow cuſtome of groſſe eaſe. Theſe worthies, I ſay, thus truſting to their bold and confident courages, ſet vp their reſt, either to follow &amp; acquire that which ſhould become profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in a communitie to the whole ſocietie and company, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to returne backe, or once to thinke of the ſweetneſſe they had taſted by their former varietie and plentie. God, who euer proſpereth the moſt worthy portion of his grace, which ſetteth forwards it ſelfe to vertuous and induſtrious acquirements, preſented in ſhort time vnto their view, helpes before that time vnknowne, but yet not without danger, nor ſo ſucceſfull, but ſtill they ſhould worke themſelues into the poſſeſſion of them, by hardie, painefull, and manlike endeuoures. After they had through this good gift &amp; enclination of Fortitude, bin brought to the diſcouerie and knowledge of theſe likely meanes, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and progreſſe in this vertue, they dared withall to aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and with a voluntarie courage ſet vpon difficulties, which ere that time for want of proofe-making in themſelues, they had not maſtred. Setting at the firſt, fierceneſſe againſt feare, and extremitie againſt extremitie, and ſo by the aiding hand of God eaſily conquered into their obedience and vſe, firſt wilde and forcible creatures, then others that were vnder the maiſterie and command of them, before that time the matter of their ſpoile. Theſe worthies thus returning with profitable reliefe to their droanes at home, who notwithſtanding their owne deffects, were yet able to conceipt and admire the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the conquerours by their atchiuements, moſt mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately on the ſuddaine they extolled and lift them vp beyond the credit and beleefe, that they could be leſſe then Gods in <pb facs="tcp:21420:10"/> compariſon and diſtinction of doings, being brought on at the firſt by theſe motions and affections of ioy, there was no doubt in continuance they would be ſetled in opinion to receiue and reuerence them for no leſſe then Gods in deed. After, by this ſupport of courage, they had gone thorough and accompliſhed matters ſufficiently behouefull for the common bearing out of neceſſities; they then caſt another about preſently with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, how to encreaſe and make permanent their yong and new begun world ſtrongly reſoluing with themſelues afreſh, that now it was no leſſe expedient, with lawes and manners to faſhion them how to liue, then before it was needfull to ſeeke out neceſſaries to maintaine life. After they had entertained and taken into counſell the prudent and conſidered vertue, you may then thinke they gained by degrees, into matters which haue bene in differently from one time to another deliuered ouer, as may appeare by the benefits we haue receiued from them which were immediatly before vs. Now amongſt thoſe that were thus prouoked and prepared through the force and facultie of Fortitude, after they had exerciſed their deſires vpon ſuch hard and laborious things, as before I ſhewed to be out of their powers, there was alſo in the company of theſe few, one principall man, whom I would haue you to vnderſtand, in the ſight and beholding of the other did that aboue the reſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they were rather miniſters of aides and obedient helpers, then any way able to equall: to whom they did both in their expedition abroad, and alſo euer after in all places, for his chiefe worthineſſe, attribute dutie vnto. This princely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, being more intire and fully poſſeſt with the height of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, whether by the benefit of nature, or by the ſpeciall indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods grace, with abſolute partes, he by all their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents had princely powers ſet vpon his ſhoulders, and by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall voices, was choſen and inſtituted their Duke and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to go before them in all manner of concernings, aſwell of warre and conqueſt, as alſo to be their vpholder, conſeruer, and commander in all matters of ciuill inſtitution and derecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now after all eyes were faſtened on him, and all hearts bent at his deuotion, ſuch as would not forſake their retchleſſe <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21420:10"/> ſlouth, but ſtill haue wrapped themſelues within the ſpoile of others labours, ſuch at the length by his aſſignement, were appointed places to ſerue in, according as euery one was ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, diſpoſed, or more or leſſe apt to performe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge truſt and ſeruices to be committed vnto them.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> Surely Sir, you haue ſpoken ſo darkely, that for the thick ſpleigh of boughes and broad leaues of this tree, I cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne your meaning. <hi>Huddle.</hi> Thinke you I go about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue you with darkeneſſe of words? If a field be ſaid to haue eyes, a wood may likewiſe haue eares. But whether you heare me not, or liſt not to beleeue me, the likelihood hereof ſhall carrie me to credit the ſame, knowing that matters of leſſe proofe and more vnlikely trueth, haue bene receiued from worſe grounds and beginnings then this commeth from. But you may ſee how the loue I beare you hath carried me to clime vnknowne hauntes, and ſuch difficult pathes, as there are no ſteppes or traces left mee to follow; therefore you may ſay, it is like to proue a hard iourney to a weake tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Now I better remember my ſelfe, I haue read many ſtories agreeing with your worthies in their notable deedes and exploites, done by couragious and bold attempts. <hi>Huddle.</hi> I will not ſeeke to winne you by extremitie of ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but leaue you to the libertie of your owne better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauings. To keepe whole the vnderſtanding of the matter, I will come to that which ſhall neerelieſt agree with that I ſaid before. After this principall Worthie was enthronized by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, himſelfe was alſo addicted and diſpoſed, for the better conſeruation of all things in order, in the integritie of his iudgement and diſcernings, to conſider with rewards and dignities ſuch deſeruers and beautified mindes, as himſelfe had ſeene forward by ready and feruent diſpoſitions, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and crediting vnto them for their tryed and approoued ſeruices, ſuch degree of truſt and ſuperioritie, as might both ſtand in ſtead towards a recompence of their trauailes, and alſo the more incourage them to go on with him in perfecting things neceſſarie to vphold ſocieties and vocations, wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he had lately ſorted the whole people. Afterward, ſuch of <pb facs="tcp:21420:11"/> all ſorts as had defected and come ſhort in ſufficiencie, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme matters and places committed vnto them, ſo as the reſt receiued loſſe and hinderance by their fault or negligence; ſuch iniurious deceiuers were depoſed, thruſt downe, and diſfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed, as perſons vnfit to become the ſtrong vertues and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties beſeeming men euer after compelled to exerciſe weake things, and withall enioyned to liue out the reſt of their dayes in the company and conuerſation of women. What occaſion ſoeuer notwithſtanding vrging the vſe of them, ſuch were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer recalled nor ſuffered to execute duties amongſt men. <hi>Dun.</hi> That you may perceiue the warmth my beleefe hath catcht through your moſt excellent deſcription, I will open vnto you my conceiuing of your ſpeeches, by the proceſſe whereof I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you meane to deriue Kings and Princes from the moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall deſeruing worthy, who from ſucceſſour to ſucceſſour, haue ſtill added ornaments of rare excellencies: to the intent that thoſe who from time to time haue iſſued from them, might through their cleare and ſhining perfections be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to haue iſſued from ſuch noble, famous, and renowmed progenitours. Prouing further withall, that ſuch high prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe and meritorious parts neuer fading, but euer more and more encreaſing, haue long ſithence through the dignitie and glory of notable deeds by the hand of God, bene exalted into throne and Maieſtie wherein they ſit, hauing in themſelues through him ſufficient power and abilitie enough to nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate and make famous whomſoeuer they may pleaſe to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, appoint, and chooſe. <hi>Hud.</hi> I thinke it hath bin the warmth of gentle bloud, which beating within your breſt, hath thruſt out this formalitie you indent your words withall: could my conſent helpe towards it, you ſhould be made a gentle maiſter Scriuener, for your orderly frame of words are ſo well ſuted, that as me thinketh you haue much amended the old patterne you began with in the morning. If you miſtake me in ſence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo no worſe hereafter, it ſhall not repent me to talke of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion yet a while longer with you. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Though of my ſelfe it ſoundeth not well, yet without brag be it ſpoken, there be Gentlemen of bloud in this countrey that ſit not ſo high in the <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21420:11"/> ſubſidie booke, neither are rated in furnitures and ſetting out of men to the warres in ſort as I am. <hi>Hud.</hi> Herein you deceaue me little. I euer tooke you fitter for the land then the ſea. How can you proue a good marchant, that are not willingly pleaſed with the venture of a little without grudging, to gaine infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and continually? I doubt me if her Maieſties moſt gratious prouidence exceeded not the beneuolent reſpects you beare euen to your ſelf, you could not ſo quietly haue encreaſed your ability, nor brought your wealth to that plenty, you now enioy it, but might haue bene indangered to haue loſt ſomewhat of that you haue long ſithence through her ſafe gouernment and defence, laid vp hoords, robbing the common-wealth of the due vſes they were made and ſhould ſerue for. There are too many both vnmercifull and moſt vnthankfull men, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine and are more troubled with the departure of a from their ſuperfluitie and abounding plentie, then other good men are from their reaſonable and competent abilities, which they readily ſhew to the vttermoſt by their good intents. I partly know them you ſtretch your ſuperlatiue degree of compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at or if I do not, thus much generally I can ſay of all Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, that their forwardneſſe to haue ſuch things in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for themſelues, if need ſhould ſo require, and with ſetting out their ſonnes in ſeruices already paſt, that if you ſhould be rated, as they becommingly prepare themſelues, you would thinke your ſelfe robbed of that you beſtow in that ſort, of and for the ſafetie of your ſelfe and your goods. I confeſſe you want no abilitie with the formoſt to performe neceſſarie ſeruices, could your willing heart conſent to the ſame, as I ſaid to your owne good. I truſt for Subſidies, Gentlemens lands and their other values are more readily diſcerned, and farre more ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then your buried pelſe, laid vp for the deuill and his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe. Had you the lamentable experience but of one daies warres, which God keepe vs from, you would then call for twentie yeares ſubſidies, and bring them in as willingly as you now burie and obſeure them from the ſeruice of the realme For all your complaining, I doubt not but once in the yeare you ſquit out a commoditie to ingrate vpon the Gentlemans <pb facs="tcp:21420:12"/> neceſſitie you meane, with buying eyther his whole yeares wood-ſale, his croppe on the ground, or ſome other out-lying commoditie, that ſhall goe neare to defray your whole yeares charges, the marriage of your children excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> Had I thought your maiſterſhip would haue taken my free ſpeeches in ſo ill part, which concerned onely my ſelfe and my ready abilitie, to forward to my power my Prince her occaſions and ſeruices, I would haue forborne to haue vttered my minde, wherein I onely grieued, that any ſhould exempt themſelues or forbeare to extend their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt helpe and indeuour in ſuch good workes. My in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was not to repine at my owne eaſie charges, eſpecially to performe ſo neceſſarie a dutie. If it pleaſe you to forget my fooliſh ſpeeches and ſcattering queſtions, beginning where the matter brake off, you ſhall fauour me; in that I haue a ſpeciall deſire to heare at the full, you hauing ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie entred into the declaration thereof. You left at abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute vertues, which are the gifts of nature, and accompany Gentlemen from their birth. <hi>Huddle.</hi> Sithence by your deſire I am put in minde of complete vertues, which are ſaid to be in Princely deſcents of bloud from the beginning, and at their entrance into the world: I am contented there to beginne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. All creatures in manner that beare life, haue alſo at the firſt an inclination towards a very neare ſimilitude of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from whence they came: by which I prooue the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are in parents, deſcend wholy and without change, ſteps, or goings on, in like manner and ſort to their children, as they were indued therewith themſelues, but if the parent want the perfection thereof himſelfe, his childe may attaine vnto it, but not by natures benefit, for that the foregoing one had not the entire poſſion thereof in the time of his life. It is euident to euery vnderſtanding, that abſolute vertues neither decreaſe nor increaſe, for looke what is perfect in it owne fulneſſe, the ſame is able to enriche and fortifie what it affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and naturally inclineth it ſelfe wholy vnto: it neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, as I ſaid, becauſe of it perfection it can be no leſſe in the ſucceeding childe, then it was in the proceeding father, ſo <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21420:12"/> that the vertue moſt excellent in the one, ſhall be the ſame without exceeding or diminiſhing in the other, admitting no mediocritie, reacheth at the firſt the vttermoſt point of the vertue which was of that integritie in the former Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie. That vertue which wanted perfection in the progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, his ofſpring may attaine vnto: but it is not his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar bleſſing, as it ſhould haue bene, had it not wanted perfection in the other. Becauſe the one wanted the full and entire poſſeſſion thereof, he cannot deliuer it ouer by deſcent in bloud. <hi>Dunſta.</hi> Belike then, if the worthie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitour had attained to the tipe of all perfections, his worthie of-ſpring had at the firſt immediately bene ſeaſoned with that moſt precious liquor, according to the influence into the former veſſell. <hi>Hud.</hi> Yea vndoubtedly, but the myſterie of the perfection celeſtiall, which you rightly termed a moſt precious influence, it is too deuine to dwell vpon earth, or to be diſcuſt by mortall ſence and vnderſtanding: but the next vnto that omnipotencie, are Kings and Princes, becauſe they receiue theyr bleſſings from God directly, without other bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or additament whatſoeuer. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Then I pray you Sir, how do diuerſe without the benefit of this generous bloud, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to ſuch ripeneſſe as may make them worthie high place and dignitie in the word? <hi>Huddle.</hi> Through forward inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſpoſition, taken with the loue and deſire to immitate ſuch ſeruiceable vertues as they haue ſeene approoued and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded in others, whoſe more properly at the firſt they were, and ſo vpon iuſt cauſe, are both receiued and held wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men. In the firſt vertuous man, I ſhewed you euen now, after his good ſpeed was ſeene, and the way knowne, how he did great things, others were ſtirred vp to haue pleaſure and delight in the like, yet ſuch alſo as were better endued, and of a more ready motion then the reſt. For all could neither be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited by example; nor forced by compulſion to needfull and concerning duties, to the pleaſuring of themſelues. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> By this reckening, wiſdome to forethinke is not the leaſt helpe both to ſeeke and alſo to become great places attained vnto. <hi>Hud.</hi> All my ſpeeches haue tended to that end and purpoſe, <pb facs="tcp:21420:13"/> Yet firſt I ſhewed you, how bold courage did rouſe and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken men from out the cradle of ſecuritie, before they were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by conſultation: euen then alſo had they failed of reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to enterpriſe and breake through diſficulties, ſuch alſo as perhaps were repugnant vnto reaſon, and aboue that wit could perſwade to be poſſible, then all had fainted, and nothing had bene atcheiued. Now wit, arte, and counſell, which you ſpake of right now, might haue ſerued them to prolong their plenty, and to haue held them ſtill in eaſe, to haue leſlened and made away by deuiſe, ſome of their ſuperfluous and riſing numbers; but the ſtrong vertue was firſt, and it preuailed to beſt purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and bleſſings. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Now ſir I beſeech you, ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the defects that were found in them that neuer came forward. <hi>Hud.</hi> I haue promiſed ſo to do. You may imagine, that while the ſunne is oppreſſed and ſurcharged with cloudes, her vertue of comforting is for the while hindered; but when ſhe hath out wrought them, and broken thorough the black priſon, her light is then cleare, and her operations effectuall. Likewiſe, whileſt wantonneſſe, belly cheare, and other entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling delights, held men back from the vſe and knowledge of themſelues: till I ſay, the maiſterfull ſpirit had by maine force, ſpoiled and driuen away all impediments, they could purchaſe no freedome nor reſt contented, vnleſſe they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo to make a through conqueſt of themſelues, then which there could not be a greater victorie. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> A faire and a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous generation of worthy men, fit to take example at. <hi>Hud.</hi> The princely worthy, that had bene the cauſe of the beginning and diſcouerie of all theſe things, through his ſearch and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturous inquirie, after I ſay he had laid theſe faſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, ſufficient both for their owne foundation, and alſo for continuing their ſucceeding poſterities, making alwaies the end of one diſcouerie, the beginning of another, and after him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for all theſe benefits had bene deſeruedly crowned and holden in due honor and regard of the reſt, at once he amended all their eſtates, bringing the number of ſuch as were out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, into order, by prouiſion as aforefaid, of ſuch neceſſaries ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, as nothing but the iuſtice and diſpleaſure of almightie <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21420:13"/> God could bereaue them. Now to iumpe with your deſire, I will directly ſhew you who were the
<hi>pecora campt,</hi> to whome for their vnwillingneſſe little or nothing was poſſible. You muſt alſo remember, how at the firſt I tolde you, few by nature and their owne ready inclination were warlike, yet by inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and imitation, ſhaking off and expulſing the firſt diſeaſe called ſlouth, many were faſhioned and inſtituted, by the deſire they had to folow the diſcipline of the firſt worthies. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, there remained a ſculke of ſuch, as neither care nor caſtigation could amend or make able to entertaine other purpoſe or deſire then at the firſt. Beſides, to increaſe their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber &amp; ſort, there were diuerſe whoſe courages abated, degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating and declining by immoderate and intemperate contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, thorough which they corrupted and loſt their firſt bloud and eſtimation, differing in a manner altogether from the good reſolutions to vertues, which at the firſt, either themſelues or their aunceſtors had bene raiſed vnto: who rather then faile, by erudition and tradition, for the honour of their owne firſt vertues, were deſirous to haue had their poſteritie aſſumed and admitted vnto them. To make along tale ſhort, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the euening ſtarre hath made the ayre temperate and fit for vs to trauell, you muſt ſtill note the number that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſubiected themſelues ſo much to inordinate libertie, that no decree could demonſtrate vnto them any thing ſufficient to reſpect a more ciuill and perite life; but that they would repoſe themſelues vpon pleaſures, which they deſired ſtill to hold, as their defence and fafegard, to keepe and defend them from the perils of their life. Playing the tyrants thus with themſelues, ſuffering baſeneſſe to beare all the ſway, according to beaſtly fantaſie and licentious appetite, ſuch neuer came at all forward to better themſelues, neither by reputations for vertues, which they were careleſſe to poſſeſſe; nor for deſire they had to purge or ſegregate themſelues from the ſoft vices they were firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected withall: neither yet were at all moued with the felicitie they ſaw the reformed to liue in: nay the commandement and reprehenſion that was vſed for their amendment and bettering preuailed not in them. Now comparing the number of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:21420:14"/> who neuer admitted excellencies, with thoſe that fell away and decreaſed their worthy parts and qualities, without reſpect or care to put on againe the habit and dignitie of well doing, you may well finde the cauſe, why ſo many vnworthy, are at all times found amongſt ſo few bleſſed and happy men, who are endued with excellent diſpoſitions of themſelues, to do and to diſtribute good and wiſe things. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I pray you ſir ſuffer me yet to aske you this one queſtion more, whether you thinke courage or counſell the more beneficiall vertue, to aduance and ſet forward actions of greateſt moment? <hi>Hud.</hi> I am content to vnderſtand you by your meaning, and ſo anſwer to that I think your deſire is to know, which of the twaine ſhould be the firſt or more principall vertue to become great things. If wit ſhould be of more force then courage, who ſhould keepe the Woolfe from the dore? the folde alone cannot defend the ſheep, neither one ſheepe helpe another. If courage were not the preuailing vertue, wit would perſwade him not at all to go to the warres, and ſuffer there all indurances, depriuing vs of ſuch laudable things, as we might elſe at eaſe and in ſafetie inioy. Wit can teach, it is more ſafe tarrying at home, ſleeping in a whole skin vpon a ſoft bed, then to lie in a waterie ditch abroad with blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wounds. Wit can ſhew you, that it is better to ſtand by a fire of ſtraw, making Mault in a drie houſe, then to ſuffer cold, thirſt and hunger vnder the wide open welkin. Wit taught
<hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſes</hi> rather to counterfet madneſſe, and to choake himſelfe with his countrie ſmoake; then to change ſweete and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous pleaſure for the ſowre aduerſities that are ſuffered in the warres. Wit waiting vpon courage, that is a conſonant thing to compaſſe and make all vndertakings fortunate. Fortitude ſhall haue much to do, to make wit ſhake of his feare, forget his trembling motions, and to put on the armour of all proofes, called militarie boldneſſe: but when that is once on, with more eaſe he ſhall be taught the skilles and knowledges which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the tollerating and ſufficient doing hard and difficult things. After this, beſides wit muſt alſo haue conſtant perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to dare to enterpriſe, and in perſon himſelfe to go againſt dangers. Wit thus girt, it is good conferring and counſelling
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21420:14"/> with him in the field: but if naked wit be principall man there, the Drumme and Trumpet muſt ſound and ſtrike vp falſe alarms to daunce baſe daunces: firſt on a little forwards, at the firſt he cryeth, then by and by retire: the reſt muſt be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced backward, which is called a baſe daunce, eſpecially in the field. Naked wit can bid others be bold to fight, and runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way himſelfe, he can giue counſell, and direct to begin well, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is moſt need to go forward, defecteth euen in his owne precepts, ſuch tyrants can lead men into the field for their owne good, vnder the ſtandard of wit. To ſuch faire warres I thinke a man might intreat your companie. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Alas Sir, hard lodging and bad diet would be as good as a murthering piece to kill me out right. Yet for one day I could be content to ſee faſhions amongſt them with a quarter of a cold Pig, and an
<hi>Aquavita</hi> bottle vnder my girdle. <hi>Hud.</hi> Nay, I can aſſure you, the warres and a colde ſtomack will neuer agree: at theſe yeares, you and I will pray from them that may. To martch in Armour, and to go vnder the waight thereof, would breake our bones, being, as they are, cold, drie, and marrowleſſe. <hi>Dun.</hi> My ſonne telleth me, it is nothing now a daies to be a ſouldier, for they neuer come to pitcht fields, as they were wonte in our olde Engliſh warres, when the deuiſion of houſes was. <hi>Hud.</hi> Is your ſonne a Fencer that wayes to; I thinke he be an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall man. But I pray you what warde hath he to beare of a Musket bullet? it muſt needs be with his legges, for his hands I know are not Piſtoll proofe.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> I confeſſe thoſe gunnes are diueliſh things, and make many men runne away that other wayes would not turne their heads. But when I ſaid a Souldier, I meant the Generall or commander in the warres. He telleth me many times he could diſcharge the place himſelfe, though he neuer ſaw an enemy in the face. <hi>Hud.</hi> Not vnlike, but ſhew me I pray you, wherein the commaunders office conſiſteth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that you haue heard your ſonne report. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> Marrie ſir, in ordering and ordaining the field, and in well lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his campe, neare riuers and places defended from conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious noiſome winds. <hi>Hud.</hi> What ſhall then be the Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall his place vnder him, if his Generalſhip be thus imploied<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:21420:15"/> 
                  <hi>Dunſt.</hi> He ſaith <hi>Hanniball</hi> ſupplied both the romes himſelf, and made the offices one: he alwaies when he came to ioyne bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels and prepare his fights, beſtowed his footmen vpon hils and places of aduantage, and his horſemen in the plaines and euen valleis beneath. <hi>Hud.</hi> If yong <hi>Hanniball</hi> your ſonne were chieſe in the field, his footmen ſhould be Aſtronomers or wiſards, to know when they ſhould not fight, then from the hilles to giue ſignes to the horſemen to be gone, and flie away together, and ſo your ſonne his hoaſt ſhould conſiſt of a running campe. Though I was neuer worthy to beare the name of a companion in the warres, yet vnder his conduct I could be content to refuſe the offer of a very good place and office. <hi>Dun.</hi> What office is that, and why? I pray you ſir let me know. <hi>Hud.</hi> No entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could tempt me to be maiſter of his carriages, to carrie &amp; recarrie hils and dales, windes and waters; beſides I know the great librarie that hath coſt you ſo many quarters of Corne, muſt alſo waite vpon his remoues. If that fleet vp and downe with him, well he may looſe an eye with poaring vpon his <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erilis,</hi> but with climing the Alpes as
<hi>Hanniball</hi> did, for catching an ill humor in that ſort, I dare put you in comfort and be his warrant. <hi>Dun.</hi> May it pleaſe you ſir to take a hard lodging at my houſe to night, for I ſee by the Moones leape into her wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie circle, if we ſit long here, vnwholſome dewes will be ſent downe vpon vs. <hi>Hud.</hi> Not now I thanke you, I haue ſuch bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe with my Lord that I cannot, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I come into the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey againe in winter, it is like I will bid my ſelf vpon this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiſe.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> I haue a caſe of ſome extremitie, wherin I would be glad of your worſhips counſell, might I be ſo bold to craue it. <hi>Hud.</hi> Tomorrow in the morning when my Lord is gone forth againe to hunt, I wil be ready for you, and as glad of your companie as to day. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> God keepe you Sir, as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth me, I will waite vpon your comming abroad in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>Hud.</hi> Good night neighbour.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the firſt dayes meeting.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="day">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21420:15"/>
               <head>THE SECOND DAIES MEETING.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Huddle.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O make paiment of my promiſe, I haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlipped an oportunitie with my Lord, but I hope to recouer it with my better diligence the next day. <hi>Dun.</hi> It is a buſie harueſt day al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with me, and I might ill haue bene ſpared from my worke folkes, who will make it noone till it be night, with drinking, ſinging, and lazing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the ſhock: but I had rather looſe their whole dayes worke, then to haue miſſed your worſhip, who ſo friendly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me to your hinderance. <hi>Hud.</hi> I perceiue they ſing well that worke well with you, but this faire day will make them labour like Bees to gather in your harueſt.
<hi>Dun.</hi> That ſeruant is too wicked and careleſſe, who will take his hire and leaue his worke in this ſeaſon, eſpecially when it is a ſigne of health to labour. <hi>Hud.</hi> I doubt not but you are wiſe enough to reward them according to their deſerts. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I pray you ſir, heare you any further newes of the good Earle his abiding here ſtill amongſt vs? <hi>Hud.</hi> There is nothing knowne to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie; they that would haue it ſo, hope as they did, but how it will fall out, the ſequell muſt ſhewe. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> How happie a thing were it to the common-wealth, if me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of priſe would liue in their countries to keepe the vnworthy backe. But the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of them that are and ſhould be worthy, encourage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to take their places, and ſuffer them ſo greedily to catch vp, what they careleſlie let fall. Should you but ſee what mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket croſſes, ſome mens houſes are made with baskets to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all maner of things that euery ſeaſon affordeth, you would thinke it more then time to wiſh better men in their places: <pb facs="tcp:21420:16"/> falſe cuſtome hath made wantons of thoſe that are of no deſart nor need<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on purpoſe to bereaue them that want, euen of that they bring vp and ſhould liue by. Nay the fooliſh world is made more afraid, and ſtand in greater a we of theſe proud ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, then they are of God himſelfe, by which idolatrie they are become more religious towards men then to their maker. Should ſuch men not performe to their belly Gods a Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas ſacrifice of Honie, they would thinke their Bees would die in their Hiues, or flie away &amp; forſake them at ſwarming time. If not of Brawne and all manner of wilde foule at Chriſtmaſſe, their yong ſtores would become foule, and die of the kernels eare winter paſſe. If not of Veales and Lambes at Eaſter, their cattell ſhould rot and die of the murrion or read-water. If not of Pigeons &amp; greene Geeſe at Whitſontide, their yong flights ſhould be ſtarued in Catlock moone, and their ſtubble Geeſe flie ouer their houſes at Lammas, and be no more ſeene. If not of Cherries, Strawberries and Peares at Midſommer, let them looke for Caterpillers and Summer-winds, to blaſt and deſtroy their fruit ere <hi>Autumne</hi> come. Would God theſe widows mites might ſerue their turnes, then could we go to the pillers and poll our ſelues according to good father <hi>Tyndall</hi> his counſell. But there is that which farre exceedeth this, wherewithall at this time I am not a little troubled, but to recite it were need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, becauſe it is bootleſſe.
<hi>Hud.</hi> If you grow fine on the ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, ſparing to vtter your ſelfe to me, who am no wayes like to prooue a dangerous man vnto you, this daies meeting ſhall ſoone take end, and ſo ſtill ſafely thinke to my ſelfe what I had thought boldly to haue vttered vnto you, and the rather at your owne deſire. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> If you giue me leaue ſir, it ſhall ſoone ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto you, that my owne griefe and no diſtruſt in your fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, hath cauſed me to take a new breath in the matter. We can no ſooner bring vp our ſonnes to mans eſtate, but with coſtly maintenance we are faine to make preſents of them alſo: looke what would haue ſerued their turnes fiue yeares at home according to their births and friends abilities, muſt be ſpent in one yeare on proud ragges, to ruffin it out in the companie of their betters. Beſides, when we haue ſpent our ſelues thus vpon <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21420:16"/> our yonkerie, euen to that which would haue proued honeſt portions for them to haue liued all their life thorough: now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth our woe betide, they come home with conditions pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed at too deare a rate. To mend all in the end, their ſilly mothers make vp the matter with their fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d kockerings, ſtrok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with fooliſh words on this ſort; My <hi>Sam</hi> &amp; my <hi>Ierom,</hi> you ſhall go no more a ſeruing, but tarry at home with your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother. A ſonne I haue come home this other day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruing, with clothes all torne, his purſe monileſſe, and himſelfe no doubt graceleſſe. He had not bin two daies with me ere he fell vpon his yonger brothers, the true conſorts of my laboures, them he outragiouſly beat, reuiling beſides his mother and me with ſuch rakehelly words, &amp; helliſh oathes, that I feared more then in a tempeſt, the downfalling of my houſe on our heads. Not withſtanding all this, to make my greefe more reſtleſſe, his vnreaſonable and inportunate mother lieth at me night and day to make ouer and commit vnto him a little farme that I haue forſooth for his preferment in marriage, iuſtifying after her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion all his vices, which ſhe would haue me allow for vertues: the ruffianly brawles with his brothers ſhe termeth manhood, his horrible ſwearing, hoate &amp; haſtie ſtomach: his outfacing &amp; wording at me, audacitie and manly boldneſſe; ſaying the rude hinds his brothers cannot tell how to giue a Gentlman his due, that hath bin abroad and learned manners and faſhions. By her leaue he ſhall ſhew his behauiour in ſome other place, where ſuch faſhions are in requeſt: with me they ſhall haue no allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, nor himſelfe from me longer maintenance. Better I were now and then to ſuffer his remiſſe mother to miſtake a quarter or two of corne, to buy the knaue a coate with, then to haue him Lord it out thus vnder my noſe, and I to ſweate and ſwinke, to maintaine his lozelrie. <hi>Huddle.</hi> This you take in ſo ill part, is not worth your lament nor complaint. If you conſider the olde bondage and vaſſalrie men of your condition were wont to bein, you ſhould finde, that to beſtow a ſonne thus vpon a gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to haue him brought vp, were a pledge of your good will to the maiſter for the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his good, &amp; no ſuch hainous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as you make it, neither is the place as you impute it, the cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:21420:17"/> or occaſion of your ſonne his faults; for there can no Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be of other minde, but that he had rather his man had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good qualities, then one euill condition. Your ſonnes clim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing follies, to equall or rather exceed them he ſhould not ſtriue withall, in coſtly apparrell and lauiſh expences, is alſo blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy in your ſelfe, ſetting proud feathers higher in his toppe at the firſt, then you are able to reach and pull downe againe when you would. Had you ſaid, the taking of gifts and bribes, to peruert and hinder the courſe of iuſtice had bene a matter of common ſorrow, and is wont to be withſtood and helped by the preſence and authoritie of the honorable, their countries ancient benefactors, next and immediatly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Prince, then had you bene of the minde I would haue you with me to be in, by ſuch reaſons &amp; examples as I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to yeeld you. Gifts are ſaid to draw a curtaine betweene truth and the prudent light &amp; vnderſtanding of the iuſt, &amp; to make crooked the ſtraight and plaine teſtimonies and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the righteous. If bribes haue truth once in chaſe, light ſhe not on a ſtrong couert and ſanctuarie, ſuch an one as is nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to refuge the wronged, it is oddes after many wrinches and pinches giuen her in the courſe, ſhe will alſo be gathered vp and ſpoiled by her fierce purſuing enemies, which by craft and ſubtilty, can both gaine cope, and take the ſimple harmleſſe wretch in their cruell gins and mercileſſe ſnares. Golden blocks throwne in the way of iuſtice, her Chariot is in great danger of ouerturning. They therefore that thinke to do iuſtice, ſhould not ſo much as looke vpon gifts, which are ſaid to put out the eye of equitie. The ſellers and buiers thereof, are not worthy to be truſted in a commonwealth, much leſſe fit to hold place and dignitie in the ſame. In Romes beſt flouriſhing daies firſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice was ſold, then Rome it ſelfe was offered to be ſold. Two vnſatiable buiers we are ſure of, that is to ſay, craft and power. Now from viperous matricide ſellers, good Lord deliuer vs. But I hope there are none who would be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſee the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bowels of their naturall parents lie bleeding before them: but rather truſt to God, that all our Engliſh nation in generall will imitate the fidelity of our Noblemen, who I am perſwaded
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21420:17"/> are all of worthy <hi>Fabricius</hi> his minde. He hauing a great maſſe of treaſure ſent him from king <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> freely without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to do good or hurt &amp; in the time of his want alſo, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame vtterly ſetting more by his honourable freedom to be beholding to no ſtate or Potentate but his own, then he did of all the wealth of Egipt at which deniall or vertuous ſpectacle, the king admiring, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded it to be as eaſie a matter to alter the ſun from his courſe, as to change <hi>Fabricius</hi> from the ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance of honeſlie. Beſides their ſtrong reſolutions that way, I hope they be <hi>Argus</hi> eyed to behold from the Beacons &amp; watch towers of their wiſdomes, that no rage of rebels ſhall enter the realme at vnwares, to endanger her throane, that is the welfare of vs all, through whom vnder God we are vpholden. Further alſo I doubt not, but if any ſuch ſerpents come creeping in to diſperſe their venome, and to infect this ſweet ſoile, which is full of God and her benefits, they will be as wiſe as <hi>Dedalus</hi> was, with laborinths to intricate and incloſe them, ſo ſent from greater ſnakes then themſelues to endanger our chriſtian peace. Lay they all on one heape, or were they ſuted alike, the way to beware them were more eaſie But ſome time they lie lurking in fine penny graſſe, where they are ſuteably clad to beguile, for greene can hardly be deſcerned from greene. Other-whiles they lie incloſed in caues and dens, where they tarrie to mew their old skins, which by running through brambles and briers they hauing once ſhed and put off, then become they youthfull, and frolick it abroad, drawn forth by the comfort of the leaſt breath of a warme winde or ſmall ſunne-ſhine. When they haue thus diſſolued the ycie limmes before congealed and benummed in their frozen dens, then are they fit for the company of them, who cannot liue vnleſſe they be fed with poiſon. There they play the ſerpents indeed, creeping at the firſt into the hearts of ſuch as vnder the colour of deuotion, they can eaſily draw into abuſe, ſupplanting allegeance at the firſt daſh. When they haue abuſed ſuch with the infection of conſpiracie, to them they draw forth their commiſſion, whereat there hangeth the autenticall ſeale of Rome. The firſt words within the eſcript, are murther and rebellion. In the next clauſe is contained
<pb facs="tcp:21420:18"/> plenarie remiſſion, and forgiueneſſe, to any that can fleſh themſelues in the ſacred bloud of her gratious Maieſtie, or any that be eſpecially neare vnto her. Within this ſame writ not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, the vnſatiate legates are named Catholicks and pretenſaries to reforme religion, through crueltie to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed vpon the annointed of God. In the next clauſe following, there is a charge to binde by oath all to be ready, &amp; at all points furniſhed, to recouer into obedience ſuch as are fallen away from the ſtatutes and ordinances of the ſea Apoſtolick. After that, goeth on the laſt point, vnder whom they muſt ſerue; that is to wit, vnder the Archſtanderd-bearer of Antechriſt, the king of Spaine and his deputies. <hi>Dun.</hi> I truſt the ioyfull crowne that God hath giuen her Maieſtie, through her true feare and loue of him, ſhall continue her triumph in godly and plenteous peace, to fill the whole land ſtill with her benefits, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding helles ſting, and its roarings againſt her. <hi>Hud.</hi> Yea God doubtleſſe will euer let them want ſomwhat to diſapoint their wicked rages, which their commiſſion cannot ſupply, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their parcialities and factions: as appeared by the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent hand of God from heauen, ouerthrowing &amp; bringing to naught their Giant-like deuiſes; through the ſtrength and greatneſſe whereof they threatned the firmament, and thought to haue ſupplanted the very foundations and ground-workes of heauen. Becauſe you may reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber how God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded the deuiſes of thoſe that put their confidence and truſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and their owne right hands, becauſe, I ſay, you ſaw how they were ſcattered and diſperſed into diuers nations, flying before the face of the winds, no man forcing them, I will therfore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to ſpeake of the notableneſſe therof, not taking vpon me to be able or worthy to iudge wherein the ſecret determination of the Almighty alone preuailed. But now to tel you what they want and ſeeke for chiefly amongſt vs, as alſo to what conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions their drifts tend: know you that they hunt the authority of great perſons, by them to bring in a rauening monſter vpon vs, to worke our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion by a beaſt of confuſion, if there could any ſuch be found that would vndertake to bring in hungrie rauenours to poſſeſſe with cruelty what they bleſſedly enioy. <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21420:18"/> By the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God hitherto, we haue ſeen what their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturalneſſe hath wrought againſt others, and what they haue catcht for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. <hi>Du</hi> Belecue me, til now I had little thought their religion had te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to murther &amp; rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Hud.</hi> As though the deuotion of Rome had at any time other patience then to ouerthrow by all tiranny and cruelty. They hold no other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes to amend any thing that is amiſle in religion, but preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poiſoning, or other degrees of confuſion, are either purpoſed or executed vpon them that ſtand againſt them. How open a thing is it to euery vnderſtanding, to beleeue that they who go about, or wiſh to change the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie from the religion ſhe hath alwaies preferred before the ſafety of her life, that the ſame men haue not concluded and determined her death, according to the endeuors and abilities they were of. Now I hope you ſee by this commiſſion, how the fellow catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks that were, are become fellow ſouldiers, &amp; from Ieſuites, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, &amp; ſeedmen of ſedition &amp; conſpiracie. Their harmles deſire to inſtruct the ignorant, &amp; to bring back againe thoſe ſeduced ſtray ſheepe, that had wandered forth from the fold of Rome, that is alſo laid a ſleepe and changed. I remember how they dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied out the matter like <hi>Chaucers</hi> Frier at the firſt, vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſpiced holineſſe. <hi>Dun.</hi> I beſeech you ſir, expreſſe your conceit of that Frier. <hi>Hud.</hi> This holy man came ſick to a chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of eaſe, where one of his good dames dwelt, who had wont to beſtow the beſt roome and cheriſhing in her houſe on him. Shee ſeeing this drooping pulier thus diſtreſt, pitty ranne ſoone into her gentle heart, offering to him at the firſt the choiſe of ſuch things as ſhe had in a readineſſe to eate. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt a Henne was named, preſently to be killed for him. A Henne quoth the limmeter, nay good dame, God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ſhe ſhould be done to death for ſo ſinfull and wicked a wretch as I am; the liuer of a Henne gentle dame, will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice me; for alas I am a poore wretched vnderling, and no prouinciall man, neither warden of my company. At the firſt theſe celeſtiall ſeeds-men meant no hurt to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie nor her realme; but that which was more deare vnto her to holde, as I ſaid before, then her life, that <pb facs="tcp:21420:19"/> they would ſeeke to pull from her without offence <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> Thanks be to God for her godly reſolution. Happy is that bird that hath her neſt ſo ſhut vp and fenced in, that no deſtroyers can enter to ſpoile her and her tender louing ones. What con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations or hearts carry they, that deſire to ſubiect their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne to forraine Pottentates? Or how ſhould it come to paſſe, that the bonds of breeding ſhould bind leſſe, then the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt promiſes and rewards of other nations? Woe worth ſuch wicked proſelites that haue made themſelues ſtrangers and ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens from their owne countries, ſuffering themſelues to be won to other religion and obedience, then that which God and their Prince commandeth: ſubiecting themſelues to two tirants, that go about to cruſh and grinde to powder all the nations of the Chriſtian world, thinking none meet to poſſeſſe them but their owne mercileſſe ſelues. What worſe or more bluſterous diuels can there be, then ſuch as forſake their religion with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, for a deadly ſome of money? <hi>Hud.</hi> Haue you forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, how <hi>Iudas Iſcariot</hi> for the couetiſe of money, of his owne accord, betraid his maiſter? <hi>Dunſt.</hi> No verily. <hi>Hud.</hi> Then thinke that men may be drawne by means where they want true bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and right bringing vp; eſpecially when there is ſo buſie a counſell held abroad about the matter in the diueliſh conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion houſe of Biſhop
<hi>Caiphas</hi> at Rome, whither the Scribes and Phariſies ſwarme daily, crying; Let vs murther her, ſhe is not for our purpoſe. Beſides, thither reſort <hi>Pilate</hi> his ſeruants alſo, who at any conditions, are ready to be hired, to lay violent hands on the Lords annointed marked for his principall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and defenders of his infallible trueth. Nothing but mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will quench their inſatiable thirſt, as appeared by the Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines moſt irreligious ſacrificing of the Chriſtian King Henry of Fraunce laſt deceaſed; the day of which horrible deed doing, is hallowed, and called at Rome the day of the gladneſſe of their hearts, where they mingle and conferre diueliſh counſels with our men, whom they keepe there, with itching hands and tickling fingers already ſtirred vp to attempt violence againſt her, whom God of his goodneſſe thus farre hath made inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble againſt all terrors, promiſing ſtill to keepe his beloued ſafe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21420:19"/> from the danger of all practiſes and conſpiracies whatſoeuer. <hi>Dunſta.</hi> I pray you ſir recite your example of
<hi>Iudas,</hi> which I partly remember, yet vnderſtand not the matter ſo fully as I am perſwaded you are able to teach it. <hi>Hud.</hi>
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> you know, in title and profeſſion, was a familiar houſhold ſeruant with the Lord; but in affection of heart as appeared a wild enemie. He wanted no cheriſhing at his Maiſters hand, neither at any time receiued diſpleaſure of the Lord, whereby to conceiue ill opinion or to beare grudge, malice, or euill will towards him: yet rauening couetouſneſſe ſo gripte him at the heart, that he ranne headlong through couetouſneſſe into traitoriſme. Theſe Romiſh Iewes ſo reioyce when they can meete with a tragicall <hi>Iudas,</hi> that will venture to play a deſperate part, to put out both his owne eyes, in hope to take away a little ſight from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and that againſt Gods eternall determination. Such is their malicious hatred againſt God and godlineſſe, that they are neuer without men, eſpecially choſen to betray vnto death the ſacred perſon of her whom all ages and times ſhall repent the loſſe of, whenſoeuer God in his iuſtice ſhall viſite our ſinnes with that vniuerſall ſcourge and infliction. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Me thinkes the thought hereof in their bittereſt furies ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new loue, and prick the conſciences of them that go about any ſuch attempts, ſo as they ſhould not be able to continue in their madneſſe, yea the whole frame and workmanſhip of nature ſhould tremble at ſo horrible a deed of vnnaturall crueltie. <hi>Hudd.</hi> Had her moſt excellent Maieſtie carried a meaning to haue entertained diſpleaſures ſought and brought home vnto her, how might ſhe haue dilated and enlarged her kingdomes in circuit, vpon iuſt cauſes and worthy conceiuings? But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, who delighteth not in ſhedding of Chriſtian bloud, hath exerciſed her heart in harmeleſſe thoughts, defence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able delights, and aiding powers, graciouſlie contented with honors and kingdoms deſerued, not at all diſpoſed to any ſmall things vſurped. Thus you ſee, whither the zeale of my heart hath carried me to matters of an other ſort. Had it not bene for marring my Lords ſport, and thereby to haue endangered your ſelfe a leaſing, long ere this you would haue hallowed me in <pb facs="tcp:21420:20"/> from my counter-hunting.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> Your words haue ſo drawne the conſent of my heart vnto them, that euen this buſie harueſt time, I could be contented to loſe a weekes worke, and take it for the trueſt hunting I was at any graſſe time in my life. I thinke I ſhall neuer forget your Friar Ferret and his cloſe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the liuer at the firſt, without ruffling a feather of his dames Chick. Had I bin the good man, I ſhould haue coapt off the knaues priuie tithes, for cenſuring my houſe with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks. <hi>Huddle.</hi> Had you the like care to your ſoule, as ſhe had, you would beware to offend ſuch holy men. But you are one of thoſe that had rather liue well I perceiue, then to haue the Popes bleſſing. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Were I not caſt into heauineſſe with grieuing at my vngratious ſonne, I could match your old Friar with a new limmiter of later dayes, but my minde is ſo careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet vpon him and his vnreaſonable mother together, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I be aided through your worſhips good counſell, it will haſten my death, but eſpecially his mother, her fond importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie maketh me reſtleſſe both night and day. <hi>Hud.</hi> If it be <hi>equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctium</hi> with your wife now, it will weare away, as the nights and dayes grow longer or ſhorter. But I thinke you meane the vertuous ſpirit within you, which is ſaid neuer to ceaſe work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Other reſt it appeareth you want not, for meat-health, and ſleepe-health you ſeeme to haue, elſe could not your ſtomack diſtribute nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſuch parts as ſhew to be freſh and well liking within you. <hi>Dun.</hi> The hope of my reſtoring, is vnder God in your worſhip. <hi>Hud.</hi> To aske me counſaile, is to ſeeke helpe of a ſick Phiſition: neuertheleſſe, ſuch as it is, it ſhal not be wanting to my good friend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Me thought you were in minde to turne off your ſonne. <hi>Dun.</hi> Yea ſurely, &amp; ſo I thinke it beſt ſtil. <hi>Hu.</hi> Do you take it by caſting him vp to all hazards, by ſuch maſteries to calme his rough qualities? or rather thereby ſhall you not raiſe a greater tempeſt of euils more like to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme him, making him thereby a cleane alien from vertue, &amp; ſo of a prodigall child to become a graceleſſe <hi>Caine?</hi> Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons that meane well to their cures, where the fleſh is ſeuered by a greene wound, or blow new giuen, rather ſeeke to cloſe vp that tenderly which is already torne, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cut the ſame out wider <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21420:20"/> or longer, to make the patient further off from help and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Tailors in like maner do not mend one paine by rending more, but rather ſtitch vp that they found firſt broken. Clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Tinkers onely marre where they ſhould mend. When fire is all out in your houſe to a little ſparke, you do not by and by ſtampe your foot, or caſt water vpon that which remaineth, but rather ſeeke to repaire the ſame, by adding ſuch ſuccours &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſings as may renue that little. There is alſo a certaine ſparke or ſeed of vertue euer remaining in man, in ſpight as they ſay of the deuill, vnleſſe reprobacie haue ouer-run all. Seeke to find that in your ſonne: with good looking to and wiſe handling, it may take deeper roote then at the firſt, and ſo by the bleſſing of God, bring forth both branches and fruits of vertue.
<hi>Dun.</hi> Your worſhips voutchſafing ſtrong and friendly aides to my weake cogitations, oppreſſed with weariſome doubts, haue put me in more comfort then I feare me I ſhall finde cauſe to hope for in him.
<hi>Hud.</hi> Let it not repent you to play the wiſe father, gaining him by little and little your ſelfe. If you had a hay barne, or a mault-houſe craſed, or leaning too much to the one ſide, you would not in a rage pull it downe and burne it, but rather vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derprop it with ſtuds and timber crouches, till you were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to build it vp againe. Can you not with the ſame pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vſe remedies and meanes to ſupport your ſonnes infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties till you may frame them better to your mind? Though you cannot at the firſt make him good, do your beſt to abate his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils; then ſeeke to prouide how they alſo may do the leaſt hurt. One while vſe the authoritie of a Father, another-while the commaund of a Maiſter, at another time the loue of a friend. Thus you ſhall haue cauſe to hope better of him by holding in his cheekes, with the ſnaffle and raines in your owne hands, then by ſending him to ſeeke wilde aduentures with this ſhort paſport; Go be packing &amp; ſee thou hang thy ſelf quickly. <hi>Dun.</hi> Surely ſir, his owne conditions are like enough to be his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to Newgate, and from thence without a paſport he ſhal be ſafe conducted to Tiburne by a ſort of honeſt men, who wil not ſtick to cut downe the hangman and him both for their coats. For me to ſeeke vertues in vice his ſtore-houſe, it were fooliſh <pb facs="tcp:21420:21"/> to beleeue, and dangerous to follow. He that hath catc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to liue at his owne luſt, little thinketh that the authoritie of a father belongeth to him. By that he eateth, drinketh and ſleepeth at my coſt, ſo farre hereckoneth me to be his father but farther he neither eſteemeth nor regardeth me. Sithence his peeuiſh mother will not ſuffer my black Oxe to tread on his foote, I will ſend him where he ſhall be glad to draw in the black Oxe his yoake. I heare there is a preſſe forth for men to ſerue the Queene, God willing I will make ſuite to our deputy Lieutenants that he may be one: for it is the beſt free ſchoole I can finde to prompt wit into a braggard foole. <hi>Hud.</hi> Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, I am beholding vnto you for your ready ſpeeches, not borrowing you phraſes abroad amongſt flatterers you tell me it is fooliſh to beleeue, and dangerous to follow my counſell, it is maruell you leſt out your prouerbe, how euery man can rule a ſhrew ſaue he that hath her. The difference betwixt you and me this while hath not held, whether he were my ſonne or yours, nor and if I were in your caſe, it muſt of neceſſitie follow I ſhould be of your minde. By the like miſtaking you may nextly charge me to bolſter out your ſonne in his miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours againſt you his Father. Becauſe we are in a Parke, I will vſe a hunting terme, and ſo make away the game thus, wherein your ſelfe ſhall ſtill be iudge. See therefore in few words what I go about, which is to haue you conſider, whether it be better in time to foreſee, then after to ſorrow without remedie. My ſelfe am alſo a Father, and know the effects of nature. Therefore though the caſe be your owne, ſee you prooue not partiall nor wilfull, playing <hi>Demia</hi> his part, to be extreame againſt reaſon. Further, in truthes behalfe I coniure you not to be conceited, thinking nothing well ſaid or done, but what your ſelfe do or deuiſe. It is not your ridling with the one Oxe his treading, and the other Oxe his drawing, that muſt caſt a father head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into a rage againſt the ſonne, but rather it fitteth you bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, diſcerningly to looke vpon him with your owne cleare eies, and not to behold him with your wife her weake and glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſight, nor with the worlds dazeled ſhadowes, but I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him in a pure and right vnderſtanding of your owne; then
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21420:21"/> may you examine in differently whether your ſonne haue that in him you neuer had when you were of his yeares: or whether in your conſcience the ſame might not haue chanced vnto you, prouoked and miſ-led by the like vnworthy occaſions. Then adde a regard alſo to the poſſiblity and likelyhood of remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them by your iuriſdiction and example, impoſing alwaies vpon him things conformable to his nature. If a Phiſition can cure a ſick man well may you recouer a whole man. Wiſe Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions neuer giue the ſick patient any kinde of medicine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out choiſe but rather ſeeke chieflie to match their medicine to the qualitie of the ſick his diſeaſe. Wherfore think not to frame a rectitude of life in your ſonne, by applying vnto his nature inconueniences. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Where a matter is thus plainly ſet out, a blind man need not erre in iudgement, vnleſſe he will be falſe to himſelfe. I am bound not only to thanke your worſhip, but rather compelled to recken you the diſpoſer and author of my ſonnes and my health. Where you conditioned with me to looke vpon him with my owne eyes, therby I am put in minde to thinke him preſent, and to ſtand directly before vs: for no childe can more nearely reſemble a father in outward linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then he doth me. His better conditions according to your declaration in the Gentleman of bloud, are I thinke bred with him alſo, he hath them ſo rightly from me: but his euil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours, they at no time had cuſtome or priuiledge in me. Yet I muſt confeſſe, there wanted no proneneſſe in my owne diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ready minde, to haue entertained or ventured on the like: but ſuch a diligent father I had to keepe me vpright from ſwaruing, as I am perſwaded was not eaſie to be found. His manner of faſhioning and ſubiecting me fauourably vnto him, to introduct and make me afterwards to ſtand in his good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, was of this ſort. Had I bene complained of for doing ſhrewdneſſes in the time of my waggiſh youth, himſelfe would chearefully haue excuſed my negligence, had not my fault bin too manifeſt an euill Thorough which he would alſo take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to breath ſuch good things vnto me, as my tender yeares might beſt brooke. Shewing withall, what he miſliked in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and what he required at my hands, together with the honestie <pb facs="tcp:21420:22"/> he would haue me reſpect. By which the loue he held me in was more, then an awe to hold me back from committing what might diſcredit me vnto him. In his abſence likewiſe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other profit was alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming towards me, by directing his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to note vnto me, the euil fame that ſuch of mine acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances were of, as had robbed by the high way, made ruffianly frayes, or through any other ryots, had outraged againſt lawe. They were in like ſort commanded, to ſet out to the vttermoſt vnto me, the notoriouſneſſe of ſuch yong mens parts, as had prodigally waſted their patrimonies, extinguiſhing thereby their ſucceeding poſterities, robbing beſides their anceſtours and themſelues of worthy name and fame. Thoſe abiect and contemptuous wickedneſſes thus demonſtrated vnto me, faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ſuch a forme of obedience and feare to beware in me, that I thought my ſelfe ſtraightly bound in duty, to ſhew the newes hereof to my Father at his home comming, to glad him, with my miſlike of all ſuch crimes, as the obligations and pledges of my owne weldoing, by my deteſting them, thus accuſed and condemned vnto me, who could by no colour of excuſe be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. This would haue ſtroken ſuch a preſent ioy into his heart, to heare me giue ſentence of ſuch impenitent caſtawaies, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed his no ſmall fauour and grace towards me. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this to obſerue me thoroughly, that no fraude or guile might be intended, by ill diſpoſition againſt my well doing, through his indulgencie, when I faulted in deed againſt theſe preſcriptions, without tranſlating his accuſtomed countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or outward affections towards me, he would wiſely and profitably I muſt confeſſe for me, conſpire with my Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter to giue me the vttermoſt rigour of his iuſtice. Which done, I bewraying by my lookes whoſe hands I had ben vnder, my father ſtraight in my ſight, and hearing, would ſo rebuke and take vp the falſe Grammarian for admitting ſuch ſmart figures into his ſchoole, that I thought my ſelfe euer after paſt whipping, till the next examining day, then my fathers par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don came euer after my execution. Now ſir, when I grew vp nearer vnto mans eſtate, he let me haue all ſuch things in my power, as were fit for me to be truſted withall: Euen then alſo <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21420:22"/> himſelfe, carrying a reſpect vnto ſuch things as he thought might miſcarrie and perriſh for want of experience and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernance in me. Thus continually I was held in ſuch loue and delight in him, that ſo long as I might, and while he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I could neuer finde in my heart to depart from him. But had not the good temper of your ſharpe counſels, opened a cranney in my flinty fore-head, the ſweet &amp; pleaſant thought of theſe things, had bene loſt in me for euer, they being as faſt locked vp in my forgetfull and dull head, as the marrow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my boanes. <hi>Huddle.</hi> You do well to ſhew me my faults, and the difference in compariſon betweene you and me. The heart of a foole flyeth out at his mouth, but the mouth of a wiſe man is locked vp in his heart. Notwithſtanding, I am well enough pleaſed and contented, to be open breaſted to my good friend; concluding this matter thus: ſithence you cannot like a God, diue and looke into your ſonne his heart and meaning; by the light of reaſon haue recourſe to that you may ſee.
<hi>Dunſtable.</hi> Your worſhip hath ſeaſoned my heart with moſt wholſome and expedient teachings, ſo as now I finde that part of my minde whole, ſound, and fitte to be pierced, which euen now for the ſoreneſſe and greefe made by a freſh wound, I could not ſuffer nor abide to be touched or come neare. <hi>Huddle.</hi> It is your pleaſure to attribute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me more then I deſerue, but to giue you your due right, I haue not talked with a man this great while, that was ſo well furniſhed with ſufficient matter, in himſelfe contained, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare all his preiudices and hinderances. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> Now Sir, I would I might put you in minde of your London newes, for I am ſure according to your accuſtomed manner, you haue frequented and vſed the ordinaries where they are to be heard, and thoſe of all ſorts. <hi>Huddle.</hi> I confeſſe I haue delighted and taken much pleaſure in ſuch places: and the rather, for their companies ſakes, which were the occaſion of my ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Now they bee worne away and gone, my fantaſie to frequent ſuch houſes and ordinaries, hath alſo ceaſed: yet this laſt tearme, through ſome certaine occaſion, I was at one. But my entertainment there pleaſed me not ſo well, as that I
<pb facs="tcp:21420:23"/> could be intreated or inuited thither againe. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Why I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you ſir, are they not ordered in meat and attendance after the ſeemely ſort they were wont, or elſe are not the company pleaſing vnto you? <hi>Hud.</hi> To ſay truly, there wants no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance in thoſe that keepe them: and as for the company that vſe them, there can be no more choiſe Gentlemen, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company and delight the beſt Lord in a land. Yet it was my ill hap the time I was there, being a meere ſtranger to the whole preſence, to be ſet vpon, by one who was crept in, vnder the countenance of ſome young maiſter, that was deſirous to trie what ſport a Canarie birde could make for a blancht Almond, (at his owne finding fed with huskes.) Had his diſcretion bene any thing, his wit might haue bene tollerable.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> It is very likely, ſuch free places muſt ſometimes be peſtered with ſuch perſons of neceſſitie, to offend ſome on purpoſe, to delight o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome, making alſo a ſhifting liuing of their baſe profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I remember <hi>Terence</hi> ſaith, that refreſhing by meats, drinks, and other money coſts, will make a bold Paraſite impudent. And <hi>Plautus</hi> ſaith; God haue mercy hunger-ſtarued belly for ſuch forlorne ieſts. There can hardly be found a more inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fault, that may concerne one man to another, then for him that hath wit, to make himſelfe madde with outragious folly, offending them that giue no cauſe. How do they pull their meate out of the fire, that ſo confirme themſelues fooles for one dayes dinner? Now you being a ſtranger vnto him, and without offence in your ſelfe, I can but maruaile, how Adam Meri mouth his voluntarie could runne vpon you. <hi>Hud.</hi> The principall matter I thinke was, he found himſelfe ſtrong to ſet vpon, and my ſelf of leaſt ſhew in the houſe, and ſo the weakeſt to reſiſt.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> What a miſerable thing is it, for one that hath wit, to giue himſelfe leaue groſely to offend; or for a man to do hurt with commendable things marring a good wit, with a rebrobate tounge? I long to heare how he could pick out his commoditie from out you, whether by prepared matter on purpoſe deuiſed againſt ſome one that vſed the place and was wanting, or how otherwiſe I beſeech you to ſhew me. <hi>Hud.</hi> I can coniecture no other thing, but the very contempt of me in <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21420:23"/> compariſon of himſelfe. For without my ſpeaking to him, he began to praiſe the Satten of my cloake, the ſame you ſaw me weare yeſterday at my Lords: ſaying, it was very durable ſtuffe, and as he thought by the faſhion, not vnmade this hundred of yeares, neither of my owne beſtowing on my ſelfe, but rather left me as an heyre-lome from my anceſtours. To this I gaue no eare at all, to ſhew how vnwilling I was to match my ſelfe with ſuch a vice vpon the ſtage, with him to become guiltie of offending the Gentlemen, who deſerued better to be pleaſed at my hands, for good ſhew of curteſies by ſalutations giuen me at my comming in amongſt them. Notwithſtanding my gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing back and forbearance, at the firſt enterance of dinner he carrowſt another full mouthed ieſt vnto me, remembring in his cup, the yeoman of my wardrobe, whome he ſaid had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the leaſe of a very good farme, for his well looking to the monument on my backe. Then to ſatiſfie the Gentlemen, that I had deſerued to haue no ſuch counterfet badge pinned on myſleeue, I anſwered as neare vnto the propertie of his ſpeech as I could (not hauing had to do with the like Hare-headed fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low before) that it was not onely neceſſarie to haue a good thing, but alſo expedient to vſe it well. By occaſion of which ſpeech, altogether againſt my will, he was trained into a vaine of his owne idle and lewd ſpeaking: inſomuch, that a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by whom I ſate, offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with the tediouſneſſe of his vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent communication corrupting honeſt behauiour, whiſpered in my eare, that it was a monſtrous thing to ſee ſo young a man want his teeth. Whereat I meruailed not a little, knowing by the others continuall gaping he could not chooſe but ſee them. To take away my doubt, and to ſtop his lauiſh proceeding in odious ſpeaking he ſaid: that Pies and Dawes did chatter, &amp; make an irkeſome noiſe in the time of their feeding, but men, who were indued with reaſon, to moderate the vſe of things was not the cuſtome amongſt them, in ſuch offenſiue ſort to exerciſe their toungs. He being by this caueat put out of the pace wherein he was wont to poaſt without a guide, became dumbe, and as it were tired at the inſtant. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Such a waſpe I haue heard <hi>Ihon Pace</hi> was, whoſe rending of ieſts within the <pb facs="tcp:21420:24"/> liſtes coſt his fleſh much torment in earneſt: yet he remained all one man for the whip could not come at that by racing the fleſh, which through cuſtome was crept into the bones. <hi>Dun.</hi> If he could haue iuggled withall, there had bin ſome pleaſure and delight to haue bene taken in him <hi>Hud.</hi> If that would make you mery perhaps he could both do that, and run vpon a roape alſo. If you liſt to make experience, it is poſſible you may meet him on Salisburie plaine, to play faſt and looſe with your Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe-faire budget. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> For my part, I had rather heare tell he were faſt tied vp where I could wiſh him then in any place let looſe where I may haue to do. Had there bin none by laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to haue ſupported his groſſe rudeneſſe, who are as good as commiſſions ſealed to ſuch companions, himſelfe would neuer haue bene ſo palpablie groſſe eſpecially hauing ſuch a wit as you allowed to be in him euen now. But I pray you ſir, was not his coate made of Scogging his faſhion? <hi>Hud.</hi> I proteſt I vnderſtand you not. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> Not to come out at the back dore vpon you, in plaine meaning, of this ſort and faſhion was alwaies Scogging his coate made. Whatſoeuer ſhape or ſtuffe the reſt of the garment had, the ſleeues were alwaies one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame ſhot the other exceeding long, which gaue the world to vnderſtand, he was neuer without a long wit, and a ſhort diſcretion. Beſides him there are diuerſe yet of my knowledge. who make it their full felicitie to ſcorne any man his ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, whoſoeuer iumpe not rightly with them in all their loftie tricks of waſtefull conſuming. But this Paraſite, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure to you, meant to make ſome Gentleman in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany his owne, for whom he prepared himſelfe to be laughed at. Without doubt, me thinkes Gentlemen in deed ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no ſuch beaſtly wits to make gaine of them. I haue heard there are a ſect and company of them, who haue a ſpeciall reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting place, called Scorners hall, where there are created Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, wardens and other inferiours, all of one liuerie and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie.
<hi>Hud.</hi> It cannot be choſen, but their rents come in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie eaſilie.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> I will ſhew you what prefferreth them, and how men of this facultie are choſen to office. <hi>Huddle.</hi> I thinke I can ſaue you a labour, vnleſſe it be otherwiſe with them then <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21420:24"/> in all other companies, for they are preferred and choſen as they follow one another in time and abilitie of gettings. For my part, I ſee not why plenty of ſcoffes and ieſtes ſhould not make free, and promote to office, any forrainer in this facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Well ſir, you need no guide to beate your pathes, who can chalke out your owne way ſo perfectly your ſelfe: yet it ſhall not repent me, to ſtirre the ſtearne in a calme, to keepefreſh a more worthie Pilote, to bring the ſhippe into a ſafe porte when a ſtorme ſhall ariſe. <hi>Hud.</hi> The yeare goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, ere you can bring the Bride from out her tyring houſe. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> At once to bewray the ſimpleneſſe of my meaning, without coloures or imbrodering, when the principalleſt of this miſterie hath bene collocated in the higheſt dignitie, as to haue ſitten in ſcorners chaire, then all fantaſticall yong greene wits, muſt of neceſſitie congratulate him a farre of, ſolemnly inuiting him to dinner and ſupper taking eſpeciall heed they neither Tom, Iack, nor Wat him, as they do other apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in their liberall Arto, for it is very penall in the ſtabbing lawe.
<hi>Hud.</hi> I take them notwithſtanding their Spruſeneſſe, by your leaue, for no better then good euery dayes fooles, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none of their counſailes, not ſubiect to their babling ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> May it now pleaſe you to be put in minde of your London newes, which my ſcattering queſtions haue all this while hindered? <hi>Hud.</hi> Since I haue conſented vnto you in your other deſires, I wil not refuſe to ſatiſfie you therin alſo. There is a moſt ſtrange report made vnto the world, of a Gentleman his manner of life and death, lately deceaſed in the Cittie, the copie whereof I haue here, and muſt be faine to recite the ſainevnto you, my ragged writing being, as it is, ſo trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to reade. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> I pray you Sir, firſt ſhewe what ſort and qualitie he was of, and alſo his name, if I may be ſo bolde to deſire it.
<hi>Huddle.</hi> His parentage not of the meaneſt, in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing rather equall with the beſt, then inferiour to many within the degree of Gentlemen. His name I hauenot heard recited, but for ſect and conuerſation, a meere Epicurean Atheiſt. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> How kept he his lands? was he any wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or ſpender of them? <hi>Huddle.</hi> Surely he leſſened not the
<pb facs="tcp:21420:25"/> quantity of his heritage, but his diſſolute and voluptuous ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, were many degrees worſe then the waſting of Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Form the exerciſe of vertues, great ſummes and maſſies of treaſure are oftentimes laudably diſpended. His minner of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage was exceeding haughty, himſelfe hollow within, of ſmall diſcretion, yet of great pride to aſpire vpwards, to matters too great and tempeſtuous for him to weeld or become: placing his whole felicitie in the practiſes or rather deuiſes of new and ſtrange pleaſures, hauing neuer in any part of his life beſtowed time in the doing deeds of armes, nor at any hand willing to heare or allow the praiſes of any mans notable vertues. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> How could ſuch a one recreate himſelfe, being ſo abſolutely il, as neither to vſe good parts, nor to endure the praiſes of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men? Little could ſuch a Sathaniſt want of reprobacie, to liue thus in contempt of God and man. Me thinkes he ſhould alſo be at defiance with nature, and ſo place his delights in ſtrange, prodigious, and monſtrous things. <hi>Hud.</hi> You haue not much miſtaken the condition of the man: for euery one hath a chiefe deſire to ſome one thing or other, wherein the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light muſt be entertained, either in matters worthy or vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be beloued.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> It is oddes, the vggly vices that were like to be in him, euen haſtily ſtarted his ſoule from out his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, before the naturall and appointed time of her departure. <hi>Hud.</hi> You haue ſpoken herein more wiſely then perhaps yee be ware of: no doubt there are diuerſe things within a man, which appeare not, like as naturall cauſes do, that ſhorten, and as it were murther nature vntimely. Looke as water the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to fire, quencheth the ſame when ſhe commeth at it, ſo doth diſorderly gouernment, laying ſurfet vpon ſurfet, till e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils be multiplied ſo farre in a mans body, that remedies there can be found none, becauſe the little ſparke of life is ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed and raked vp vnder a huge heape of diſeaſes. For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſtemperature hath ingendered diſeaſe, and ſurfet nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it, continually vſing the ſame cuſtome of waſting and conſuming bloud, diſeaſe commeth to be ſo confirmed, that no medicine can come at the firſt cauſe, to take away or thruſt the greefe out of the body. Looke when the ſtomach is made heauy <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21420:25"/> by violent occaſions, appetite ceaſing, the bloud of life muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo periſh and decay: ſo death vnnaturally purchaſed vntimely deſtroieth life. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Theſe good teachings God willing, ſhall prooue counſailes to me, not to oppreſſe nature with vnruly and continuall feeding, or by ouerdoing otherwiſe to her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice. <hi>Hud.</hi> What you come ſhort of me in knowledge I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not, your words I ſee are of a phiſicall coniugation, which becauſe you pretend ignorance, I will helpe you to decline. Vnruly gouernance, you ſhall perceiue, was the confuſion and certain pouring out of this Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s life. For they that make no diſcreet choiſe of the meates and drinkes they take, neither of the exerciſes of their bodies, but ſuffer immoderate ſleepe, &amp; ſuper-abounding diet, to kill the quick diſpoſitions of their conſtitutions, which ſhould haue bene nouriſhed by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate vſe of thoſe refreſhings: let ſuch riotouſe waſters of themſelues, looke for no helpe from the Phiſitions to linger out their dayes, but rather vntimely death, or continuall help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſickneſſe. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Your words put me in minde of this old prouerbe; Either a foole or a Phiſition. He that prodigally with greedy luſt, followeth ſenſuall appetite, ſurcharging na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with continuall ſuperfluities, him I take to be the foole thus meant. He that can ordinately moderate his reſpects, by due gouernance, bridling his appetitious deſires, and vnſatiable pleaſures, contrary to this largeneſſe, him I take to be the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. There is alſo another deadly delectation, which I thinke, breedeth both fooles and Phiſitions: by that ſweete bait with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out auoidance, we are tickled on to vntimely death, vnleſſe by wholſome preparatiues of continencie, we meet and go againſt that ſore deſeaſe called lecherie. By her the ſeed of lifes beſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted ſubſtance &amp; marrow goeth from vs, which ſhould feed life, according to our firſt creation and nature. <hi>Hud.</hi> Take heed, whilſt you think to ſpeake wiſely, you erre not in greater mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe we were in hand with. There is another intellect, of farre more worthy creation in man, that was firſt faſhioned, ere that carnall fleſhly groſſe matter was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pact, who brought with it a perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyond our vnderſtanding &amp; reaſon, which ſeeth all things in vs, and her ſelfe not ſeene at all of vs: yet <pb facs="tcp:21420:26"/> through the vigor of her force, we haue a light of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of truth contained in her: which as it was firſt made, ſo ſhall it perpetually be. The other caducail fleſhly matter, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be bloud, ſinewes, veines, or the ſecret treaſure of life, ſo called by you, it had neither the firſt nor the like admirable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning that this had, therefore miſ-termed by you, to be the firſt creation or nature in man. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I haue bene ſo ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently taught already that I cannot erre herein. Your ſelfe haue prooued, that all other things, as vertues themſelues, a man may haue from his parents, who vnder God are the workers of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall things in their children, either mediate or immediately. Now ſir, for the infuſion of ſoules, I hope no Chriſtian man is ignorant, that the knowledge of thoſe deuine matters, proceed onely and altogether miraculouſly from Almighty God, yet the ſame not ſo excellent nor ſo deuine a creature from him, that it ſhould equall or exceed it maker. But I am ſorrie, the adding my fooliſh words to a matter ſo ſufficiently vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſhould take away the occaſion offered you, to ſhew vnto me the peſtilent euils, that delicious vice leacherie ſtealeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, rotting our bodies while we are aliue, offending thereby all that come neare vs, with our vnwholſome brimſtone breathes, which are faine to be abated and corrected with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders perfumed elſe could we not endure our ſelues, whoſe rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting conditions haue made theſe rammiſh faults, and not wiſe and temperate nature. You haue made ſo good ſhew of your wit in deſcribing that matter already, in ſuch ſort, that there needeth no further declaration thereof ſo that there reſteth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now, vſe of your memorie to reſtore vs to the matter we haue thus long digreſſed from. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> If you thinke good, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in your hand will prooue the remembrancer. <hi>Hud.</hi> It ſhall ſo be, but firſt you muſt imagine, it ſpeaketh of the higheſt pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of pride that hath bene in a world, pleaſing himſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with the iollitie of opinion that all concluſions, counſels and knowledges, were within himſelfe, and that he needed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conference, helpe or ſuccour, of any other mans wit, but that he was ordamed by his owne aids to reatch into miſteries, either naturall or ſupernaturall, and ſo, as I ſay, mightie enough <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21420:26"/> in his owne cunning to confirme and reſolue himſelf notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the miſterie, ſubtiltie, or intricatneſſe of any contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie whatſoeuer. The ſame eaſie and contemptible opinion he held of all creatures, the like alſo he did of God himſelfe.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> I pray you alſo let me once more ſtay the matter, with asking what religion he was of. <hi>Hud.</hi> But that I know you meane plainly, I haue great cauſe to doubt you mocke me, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring ſuch a man his religion, hearing him thus diſcribed. Vntill I haue read this writing, hold your ſelfe contented, to thinke he was an ace worſe then
<hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata; he yet at the laſt caſt while his bowels were dropping out before him, feeling the ſecret iudgements of God ſent downe vpon the blaſphemer could in the indurateneſſe of his heart, crie out and acknowledge the Galilean to be a conqueror ouer all godleſſe Giants. Thus begin the words according to the tenure of my copie.</p>
               <p>The ſtrange and monſtrous life and death, of a vertuleſſe recreant, who this other day made himſelfe a notable ſpectable to all proud loſtie tyrants, blaſphemous deuils, and voluptuous Epicures, together with his ſpeeches to his ſeruants at his dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſickneſſe, firſt taking him. Hereafter followeth alſo his ſoules farewell, and forſaking the body. <hi>Eſcript.</hi> Gogſwounds, a pox on that damned Ghoſt, I thinke the Bawde hath poiſoned me, Gogs heart, ſicker and ſicker, oh that I had the helliſh hagge here, to torment her ere I die. Oh my heart and all commeth vp together. Lord haue mercy vpon me, oh good God, oh ſweete Ieſus, helpe me, I ſhall die, I ſhall die:
<hi>Iames,</hi> go de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire maiſter Doctor to come pray with me, and for my ſinfull ſoule. Go when I bid you, and bring him ſuddainly.
<hi>Thomas.</hi> How fareth it with my maiſter, <hi>Iames?</hi>
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> I thinke he be out of his wits, he ailed nothing when he went to ſupper, now he hath ouercharged his ſtomach after his old faſhion, he cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out ſhe hath poiſoned him, ſhe hath poiſoned him. Surely he is thoroughly in to night, for I neuer knew vntill now, but a pipe of Tobacco, or a little warme water taking, would haue helpt him. Doth he call this drinking of healths? pleadge them <pb facs="tcp:21420:27"/> that will, I meane not to entertaine into my body, any ſuch cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious accidents, as bring with them paſſionate ſickneſſes, for a little ouerflowing kindneſſe. But my maiſter I am perſwaded, findes himſelfe drunke to night of the diuell his cup, and muſt needs haue a Preacher in all the haſt, to raiſe that the deuill hath throwne downe. For my part, I am aſhamed to bring a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine into ſuch a polluted place of turmoile, as my maiſter hath made his chamber Yet glad I haue gotten ſo good an occaſion to be out of the ill ſauors and ſtincks I was vexed withall euen now. But <hi>Thomas,</hi> liſt how he calleth vpon God, this geare worketh to the purpoſe, it hath made his head ſo full of waues, that by his floating prayers, and calling vpon God, I feare it will breed madneſſe in the end. He was not wont in his perfect minde to remember God on this faſhion. <hi>Maiſt. Iames,</hi> what <hi>Iames,</hi> let the knaue alone, I will none of the babling foole, hang him he will but tell me a tale of three in one, and all one, I will none of the Iuggler
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Iames.</hi> Yea marry
<hi>Thomas,</hi> now my maiſter beginneth to mend, liſt how he ſweareth and raileth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, after his old faſhion. I ſee well now there is no danger in him: I thought his head was but tottie. <hi>Maiſt.</hi>
                  <hi>Iames</hi> giue me a pipe of that <hi>Trinidatho Tobacco, lack</hi> brought me yeſterday from my brother <hi>Robin,</hi> the other is too bitter, I like it not. So, now I will prooue if I can catch a ſleepe; ſhut the dore, but go not farre from me. <hi>Thomas.</hi> How goeth the world now <hi>Iames</hi> with my maiſter? <hi>Iam.</hi> It is to be doubted he draweth homewards, he fetcheth his wind ſo ſhort: now I begin to feare indeed he hath met with ſome falſe meaſure, for he burneth ſo hoat, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be but his bloud ſweateth within him, &amp; that he is ſtung with an Aſpis.
<hi>Thom.</hi> Doubtleſſe, if your words be true he either hath eaten black pottage, or elſe hath ſwallowed downe a Cheſ nut whole, for I heare he heaueth and fetcheth hard to remoue it, but it will not be raiſed.
<hi>Iam.</hi> Helpe, helpe, <hi>Thomas,</hi> my maſter is in a ſwond. Alas he is in a lethargie, draw the Curtaines, and let in the aire. <hi>Thom.</hi> No, rather he is in a frenſie, ſhut the windows &amp; keep out the light.
<hi>Iam.</hi> Sir, for the paſſion of God, let nothing trouble you: ſhe loueth you too well, to play ſuch a part by you, who are her chiefe friend, and <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21420:27"/> all her maintainer, if ſhe were here, this would prooue a heauy ſight vnto her. Good ſir, hurt not your ſelfe, by miſdeeming her, whoſe thoughts I dare ſweare, are harmeleſſe towards you. It is but a qualme, you ſhall ouercome it well enough. <hi>Thomas,</hi> go fetch bay Friſland hither, my maiſter will ride a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and take the ayre, bid the Faulconer bring hither the Barbarie Taſſell, my maiſter will ſee her flie. I beſeech you ſir, ſhew vs ſome comfort of your well doing. Here is your chaine of Pearle, pleaſeth it you to put that on? Here is your hat with the bruche of Diamonds, will you haue it? Here is your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penioy, take her on your fiſt, prattle birde, prattle to maiſter. Here are your Monckies, play with them. Shall I fetch you your cloake with riche buttons? and if you will ſit vp in your bed, I will reach you the looking-glaſſe: if you ſaw your ſelfe, there were no cauſe why you ſhould diſpaire. But behold, in good time ſir, here is Maiſter Doctor your Phiſition come, ſpeake vnto him, and he will helpe you.
<hi>Doctor. Iames,</hi> let him alone, trouble him not, he is entring the gates of death, her ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow hath ouer-ſpred him. Thriſe before this time I haue bene with him, to forwarne him, that miſrule and diſordered diet would ſhorten his dayes He hath a dead Palſey all ouer his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, I muſt needs be gone: <hi>Iames,</hi> farewell, there is ſcant one houres life left in him. <hi>Iames.</hi> See <hi>Thomas</hi> the courſe of this world, ſpight of Arts maintenance, and Phiſicks diligence, to day an Emperour, to morrow dead. <hi>Hud.</hi> You muſt imagine the man already dead, whome the Phiſitions giue ouer. Vpon this it is to be ſuppoſed, his ſeruants they voided the chamber, and prepare their lots ready, to draw cuts how to deceiue moſt, and who to begin firſt. Like good fellowes, they muſt agree within themſelues, to part ſtakes euenly; leaſt by their falling out, the true owners come by their right. <hi>Dun.</hi> Had he made no will in his life time, to direct his goods? his lands I know can want no heires. <hi>Hud.</hi> Thinke you a man thus diſſolute could ſet any thing in order, himſelfe ſo farre out of frame? Now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the difference between the ſoule &amp; the body, at the time of their ſeparation.
<hi>Soule.</hi> Proud voluptuouſe caitife, woe worth the time I was deſtined to dwell in thee. Foule lumpe <pb facs="tcp:21420:28"/> of lead, haue I bin thy hand-maid, attending on thee night and day, alwaies quickning to my power thy ſlow and dull capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſetting before thee to exerciſe thy heauy and downward diſpoſition, beautifull heauens, the rich ſubſtance of thy omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent maker, and why wouldeſt thou not there behold ſignes and wonders, ſufficient cauſes to haue made thee know and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the power and Maieſtie of our Almightie workemai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, exceeding all Arts and vnderſtandings? How often would I haue had thee occupied in beholding the ſunne that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired glory of the heauens? Commended not I alſo vnto thy brutiſhneſſe, the innumerable number of ſtarres, rare orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ſame? In like manner opened not I vnto thee the Moone, her reuolutions and changes, and by her the whole yeares ſeaſons? Dull-eard as thou art did not I beſides prompt into thee wit and knowledge how to guide thy ſelfe vnder them? How often did I flatter thee, to haue inticed thy groſſe ſences to adore that wonderfull greatneſſe? Sturdie block, thou wouldeſt neither bowe nor incline to him. Tolde I not thee alſo in time and at the beginning, what thy fooliſh coueting liberty and contempt of his power, would bring vs vnto? By thy earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and careleſſe reſt, thou haſt purchaſed to thy ſelfe mortall death, and to me immortall vnreſt and torment. Haue I this for my reward, to be killed for quickning and comforting thee? Did I ſue to get thine eyes placed in thy forehead, to ſee before, and in time to the behoofe of vs both, that we might not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent vs after and too late? Haſt thou alſo caſt them behind thee, and made them looke downeward to delight in the old rotten and corrupt grandame earth? I was faſhioned according to the circumſpect vndefiled mirror of the maieſtie of God, and after the Image of his goodneſſe. I was conueighed into thee a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and a beautifull ſoule, but thy wickedneſſe hath giuen me my deformities, &amp; made me alſo fooliſh. I found but a little ſparke of fire in thee, not ſufficient to miniſter or to conuay needfull things to nature, to keepe her warme withall: but now I haue increaſed and kindled that little, all is on fire, &amp; ſo haue committed that I repent me of. Being ſufficient from my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, in my ſelfe at the firſt, extending now that power too farre,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21420:28"/> am become ſo weake, that I am able neither to helpe my ſelfe nor thee, letting my wilfull boldneſſe worke my diſtruction. When I entred into thee, I laboured with diligence to haue married thee vnto me, but thou wouldeſt not ſuffer me to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune louingly with thee, about matters of euerlaſting memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, and ſaluation of vs both. Thou haſt bene a heauy lumpe vnto me, keeping downe my cogitations, which were alwaies muſing vpon the holy Ghoſt, his deſcending downe into our heart, to haue warmed our frozen zeale that was ſetled there. Hadſt thou obſerued the charge I brought with me, which was for all thy makers benefits, to loue and feare him. Had we entertained, that we had bin ſafe: that louing feare would haue kept vs ſo in our makers fauour, that we ſhould haue bene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued there ſtill, vnder the ſuerty thereof, till we had bene brought back againe whence I came, to euerlaſting life. Woe worth ſuch a manſion and habitation as I haue indured with thee, the bitter and tedious fellowip I haue had with thee, hath bene voide of all ioy and conſolation. Ah fooliſh
<hi>Adam,</hi> that thou wert no better ſetled, but ſhrankeſt away at the firſt tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation, ſuffering the Serpent to take from the image of God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and loue, which thou wert commaunded to exerciſe thy ſelfe in. Thou wert too fond to beleeue one witneſſe againſt thy ſelfe, and that one a weake, and an vnſufficient woman, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom by law thou mighteſt haue excepted. Nay then too wicked <hi>Eua,</hi> that thou wouldeſt ſo haſtily credit one, &amp; he a ſerpent, thus to be taken with delight &amp; delicious ſhew, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming apparance, &amp; neglecting ſubſtance. When thou wert de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, hadſt thou none to perſwade but thy maſter <hi>Adam,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſelfe ſhouldſt haue feared and obeied, and not tempted and beguiled? Were there not works of Gods hands enough alſo beſides, and thoſe aboue thy capacitie, but thou muſt meddle &amp; intangle thy wit with that ſecret and forbidden vnderſtanding, euen wittingly therby to periſh in perill? No <hi>Adam,</hi> it was not thou, nor the Serpent that hurt me, it was the woman: we were taken out of that offence &amp; could not beware, but that we muſt be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d again with the chaines of darknes, &amp; that by a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. While I kept thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowledge to in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou riddeſt <pb facs="tcp:21420:29"/> without ſpurres, &amp; couldſt by thy ſelfe ſtrongly lay hold on the raines. But after thou hadſt troden thier paths, how ſoone wert thou fallen into <hi>Salomon</hi> his deepe pit? When thou haddeſt once ſeene the daughters of deſtruction, how long was it ere thou wert taken with their ſnares? How often did I bid thee take example by
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi> to ſtop thy eares, not at all to heare their poiſoned charmes, which had power to change thy forme into the ſhape and condition of Swine, wherein whole legions of deuils delight to dwell? Before thou wert allured by them, decent apparell, mannerly to fit and become thy body, to keep out and defend offenſiue and hurtfull things to the ſame, would haue contented thee. Now ſhirts of a hundereth marks a peece, waſte-coates of the like value, ill fauouredly to diſhoneſt the wearers, beſides other attirings of too exceeding coſt, will not ſuffice to corrupt and depraue our counterfait and diſguiſing groſſeneſſe. Before thou wert vp-growne to this vice (powring out the ſap and pithe of thy body vpon this appetitie, from which thou wouldeſt not refraine thine affections) temperate diet within meaſure, according to natures mediocritie, would alſo haue ſufficed to haue kept thy body in better health and vigour, with theſe outrages, thorough which thou haſt loſt the maiſterie of thy ſelfe. Now the whole aire, ſea, and land, beſides the compounds or additaments of Art, will not ſuffice to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold &amp; maintaine thy immoderat luſt. Before thou loſt thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and committedſt thy ſelfe to bodily and fleſhly gouernment, wholſome and nouriſhing meates, according to natures indifferencie, would haue contented thee: now all the Artificers, that belong or owe any kinde of ſuite, to the puddle houſe or foule place of carnall delights, can ſcarſely finde out or inuent one, pleaſing diſh to thy tombling appetite, thus rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp and downe in fleſhly delights. Oh how happie haddeſt thou bene, if thou couldeſt haue commanded a new creation of creatures, acceptable to thy delights, that they might haue gnawed vpon them alſo! O very plant of ſinne, that it was my deſtiny to be dwell with thee, that haſt made thy throat the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of ſinne, and thy body a denne of deuils! Euen now through the vehemencie of thy ſickneſſe, thou haddeſt a deſire <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21420:29"/> to call vpon God, but how ſoone did thy foule ſpirit within thy heart dam vp thy mouth againe? Hadſt thou not bene poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with the cuſtome of ſinning, prayers had broken the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thy aduerſarie the deuill, as witneſſeth <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Sylas,</hi> at whoſe prayers the foundations of the priſon were ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Gaole dore ſet open, and they looſed of their bonds at <hi>Phillipi</hi> in <hi>Macedonia.</hi> Had thy praiers bin effectuall, thou hadſt ſhaken off an enemy vpon the earth, and found a friend in heauen: but they were forced and conſtrained, thy deuotion being couered with the darkneſſe of ſinne. But why complaine I of thee, when my ſelfe, agreed to hearken and giue care vnto their inticings? and was as willing to corrupt the ſtate and place my maker gaue me, as thou wert? I was married to thee in thy childhood, and ere thou cameſt into the world. I had my moneths grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as thou haddeſt, and deliuered thence as thou wert. It is I that haue tranſgreſſed, and it is I that haue caſt vs both into mortall darkneſſe. Thou wert not the priſon nor Gailor vnto me. I had a large gallery in thee to walke, thou wert the chariot wherein I triumphed, but I committed the ruledome thereof to two violent guides, the one called riotous or proſperous Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the other, loftie or ſtately Pride, thorough which two Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants the deuil drew me with his charmes wholy into his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, whereas at the firſt, repleniſhed with all grace, I was ſubiect to no neceſſitie of ſinne. We thought our makers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements had bin ſtraight yoakes, too heauy for vs to beare: wherevpon the deuill, a ready helpe at all deſperate and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring aſſayes, gaue vs counſell to ſeeke libertie, and to be free as all other creatures were. An acceptable thing to obtaine, but dangerous to ſeeke by way of perdition, by wandring alone without a guide, amongſt enemies deſtitute of al aids. Through this headlong way we haue purchaſed vnto our ſelues great captiuitie. Did we ſeeke liberty? why we had a large libertie to do well, and that was all that we were commanded to do, which we called yoakes, hardly impoſed vpon vs. Contrary to this, we ſought a libertie to do ill, whither going on without retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we haue pulled a waight vpon vs, the burthen whereof is intollerable. Our vnnaturall leauing and deſpiſing our
<pb facs="tcp:21420:30"/> principall guide by furious appetite, ſtriuing to vſurpe, breake, and bring vnder, that which ſhould haue bene our Soueraigne, by forbidden deſires coueting that we ſhould not haue deſired, we are become the ſeruants of luſt, and ſo depriued and cut off from being a branch of the tree of euerlaſting life, from whence we were firſt ſprong out. How often were theſe forewarning ſpeeches pronounced vnto vs, from the moſt excellent ſpirit of the Almighty? Satiſfie your ſelues, looke what you couet is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for you to haue; you being ſubiect members from the beginning, breake not the law of your creation. How much better had it bene for vs to haue carried thankfull minds for the innumerable benefits receiued and enioyed, then thus to haue rebelled a freſh againſt the hoſt of redemption, who by his meeke ſufferings tooke away the firſt ſting of death, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed vs againe with the oile of grace? Vnworthy that we are, had we but carried thankfull minds, humbly and louingly to haue reſpected his mercifull ſufferings for vs, we had now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo found a ſtrong hold to haue riſen vp againe by. I ſhewed thee what was true, and what was falſe, which were my proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but I could neuer get thee to conſider what was to be done, and what was to be left vndone. If I could haue delighted thee, thou wouldeſt haue exerciſed thy ſelfe in me. But now I haue let goe my hold, and ſlid downe into the world with thee, where giuing my conſent to all manner of euils, we haue made our conſcience our aduerſarie, holding it downe with the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and guiltineſſe of offending, ſo that long ſince we haue left vs no poſſibilitie of amending. Had we taken heed in time, continencie had ſo walled vs in, as no enemy could haue entred his batteriſe, neither the fleſh, the world nor the deuill himſelfe, which is the chaire of peſtilence. Looke as leproſie maketh a leaper, ſo doth ambitious diſobedience &amp; fleſhly ſoftnes, breed a deuill. Thou wert of an earthly generation, nouriſhed with milke, ordered according to mans reformation &amp; inſtruction; but I was created in righteouſneſſe, diſpoſed according to the nurture and vnderſtanding of the Almighty, who will not be pleaſed with the beaſtly maners our ſelues haue faſhioned and made here beneath in this world. Thorough thee I haue bene
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21420:30"/> hindered of the augement and increaſe of grace, which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed me, yea thorough thee I haue loſt humilitie and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, the gard that ſhould haue defended me. Had I ouercome in this world, we had worne an immortall crowne; but now thou haſt preuailed, I haue loſt the ſincerity of an angelicall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and am become abhominable in the ſight of God, before whom we ſhall haue no kindred to ſpeake for vs nor any other that we haue bound by benefits and rewards, nor yet ſuch as will be afraid of our threats and commands But as we could haue none to ſpeake againſt vs in this life, no not in the behalfe of truth and innocencie: ſo now we ſhall finde none ſo corrupt to ſpeake for vs before him, who will ſuffer no bolſtered cauſes nor depending delaies to eaſe vs one whit. But there we ſhall be ſure to finde the whole quire of heauen equiuolent, to iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene good and euill, pronouncing this definitiue ſentence; Go yee curſed and poſſeſſe vtter darkneſſe, prepared for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and his Angels, where it is not knowne nor remembred what the treaſure of immortalitie is. Fortunes wanton, how much better for vs had it bin, by tribulations to haue bin wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſeparated from the voluptuous delights of the world, then to haue enioyed this liberty, thus to fulfil our appetites &amp; deſires without controleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? But in compariſon of our ſelues, we haue ſet at naught al creatures, eſpecially the poore, defying at the heart their neceſſities, whoſe accuſations, no queſtion, are gone vp into heauen, in the bitterneſſe of their ſoule, accuſing vs to the maieſty of him before whom their praiers cannot but be heard. Thus confounded with cruell &amp; immoderate exceſſe, how could we propound vnto our ſelues long life, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the means to preſerue health? Nay, what could we looke for, but ſoddaine &amp; miſerable confuſion; who preferred exceſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mediocrity? Thou wert in the right, ſhe poiſoned thee, thy tender and louing darling, that imbraced euery vaine &amp; ioint of thee, holding thee ſo faſt, that thou hadſt no feeling of thy ſelfe. It was a right ſhees part, after ſhe had inflamed thee within, made thee cold, bare &amp; naked without, to leaue thee alſo like a block, emptie &amp; hallow within, fit for nothing but wormes to creepe into. For all thy high climing, ſhe hath laid thee low enough. <pb facs="tcp:21420:31"/> Farewell, the worſt veſlell that euer good licour was put into. Corruption I ſay farewell, till we meet in hell. Whether I go vpward or downward, torment is euer before me, and the ſound of this trumpet; come ye that are dead in ſinne, to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I am but a borrowed ſpirit, thou canſt not call me back againe, wherfore without hearing thy reply, farewell. <hi>Dun.</hi> Ah deſperate mans death, in whom was all proneneſſe to euill, and no diſpoſition to do good. It ſhould ſeeme he was haled out of this world contrarie to nature, and without the conſent of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Your report of theſe newes, haue put me in minde of a ſpeach I once receiued from the wiſeſt mans mouth that I thinke was in our age, if I may ſpeake it, as I hope I may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence. This worthy Gentleman, was called in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries as I haue heard, the Engliſh <hi>Salomon:</hi> the honorable dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and place he bare here, were ſufficient approuements of his wiſe vertues. Sir <hi>Nicholas Bacon,</hi> once a famous Lord keeper of the broad ſeale: whoſe words agree rightly to prooue one part of your ſpeach, that the woman had done the hurt, which the deuill gaue ouer and could not preuaile in. His experience was on this ſort. In his yong daies, a frend of his that was like to ſuffer death, for conſenting to murther a child he had vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully begotten on a moſt wicked woman, ſent for him to the priſon where he then was: to whom this worthy Gentleman, hoping to do good, was eaſily intreated to come. At his firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into ſpeech with him, he ſtraightly charged him with the hainouſneſſe of the crime, ſaying, he thought all the deuils in hell could not haue inticed him to haue done the like. To whom he anſwered, his conciept of him was good, and no other then the truth: for it was not the deuil that had the vpper hand of him, who receaued alwaies a diſcouraging anſwer: ſo that ſhewing his complaint of not preuailing to her, ſhe gaue a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der onſet that would take no nay, as by the ſequell appeared. To demonſtrate the matter more euidently, he drew out to this honourable Gentleman, her diuers charming letters, written vnto him with ſuch termes of confident boldneſſe, as were hardly to be reſiſted in an affectionate body. Which when this modeſt Gentleman had read, ſo ſoone as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently he might, <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21420:31"/> betooke himſelfe to humble prayers, that it might pleaſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God all the dayes of his life, to deliuer him from the high and inightie preuailing temptations of wicked women. <hi>Hud.</hi> Surely a deed beſeeming a moſt aduiſed wiſe man, whom no doubt all his doings declared to be the beſt obſeruer of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mediocrity that I haue knowne: a rare matter in a man of his greatneſſe. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> But I ſhall neuer forget the horrible death and end of a moſt vnrighteous wretch. I thinke not my ſelfe a little beholding vnto you for theſe good teachings, though by the example of the moſt abſolute ill man that euer liued.
<hi>Hud.</hi> To giue me thankes, is but to purchaſe you your due from me, who haue not my ceremonies in ſo good a readineſſe. I am more like to profit ſelfe by your reports, eſpecially deriuing them from ſo well a choſen worthy, whoſe approoued example here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I will bind my ſelfe to obſerue, taking it for a generall rule, that the deuill when he goeth about to beguile man, thinketh it more meete to procure women to ſolicite for him, then to go himſelfe on the errand, as witneſſeth alſo more ſpecially the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Euah. Dunſt.</hi> Now I beſeech you to your other Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don newes. <hi>Hud.</hi> With a good will: another newes is this. There was of late, an old man in the Cittie, who decaied as it ſhould ſeeme in memorie, miſtooke the ſeaſon of the yeare, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading himſelfe he felt Aprill flowers ſpringing freſh in his withered body, thought it had bene May in Ianuary. Whervp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he ventured like a freſh gallant to marry a yong damoſell, to whom he might well haue bene grandfather. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Poore wench, ſhe was like to haue a great harueſt &amp; a little corne. But I pray you ſir, did ſhe not hood the old foole? <hi>Hud.</hi> You make ſuch haſt to your new found phraſes, that they aske leaſure for me to vnderſtand them <hi>Dunſt.</hi> The old word is ſo odious, that for my part I could be content the deed and all were out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion: but doubtleſſe, I can thinke no leſſe, but this marriage muſt needs iumpe with my meaning, for hoate and cold cannot agree together. <hi>Huddle.</hi> You meane ſhe made him Cuckold. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> I had almoſt ſaid ſo.
<hi>Huddle.</hi> Though all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods prooue not true, yet perhaps this did; and now fir to the purpoſe. This old courſer of <hi>Naples,</hi> knowing the daintineſſe <pb facs="tcp:21420:32"/> of his chaffer, tooke the way he could to pleaſe her, ſithence the way ſhe would was not ſo ready with him. Furniſhing her at the firſt with the plenty of all rich delights that the heart could wiſh, as Iewels, apparrell, and diet of the choiſeſt. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the heape and plenty of theſe gorgeous things, there was euer one thing wanting, that ran moſt in her minde, which all the cators ſhe had, could not the skill to buy or procure her. Though Fortune had not yet bene ſo friendly to affoord her longing, yet nature had ſufficiently furniſhed her with skill to diſſemble her want, ſhewing all cardes made, whenſoeuer this old yonker liſt to rage and play with her; in ſhort ſpace, this luckie chance fell out, for the deuill will alwaies helpe his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, looke whoſoeuer wanteth, they want not. A yong reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, freſh budded Aprill indeed, came by the dore, where this faire flower ſtood, in the cuſtodie and looking to of a withered impotent gardiner, whoſe ſtrength appeared ſcarſe ſufficient to raiſe the dry and light moulds that grew about this Roſe, much leſſe able to water and gage to the roote it ſoundneſſe. Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon this glaunce, he caſt with himſelfe how beſt to ſupply the wants he might eaſily diſcerne her to be in. Not truſting too much to his owne greene wit, thought it good to repaire to the counſell of ſuch a one, as experience and knowledge had made wiſe in that facultie: not hauing ſpent all his time at cards and dice, as ſome vnthrifts do, had vpon ſome vrgent occaſions bene acquainted with a cunning wiſard, called mother <hi>Ducke,</hi> a dame, who in her dayes had brooded vp no ſmall Ducklings, but ſuch rather, as were able, without putting the bill vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the wing, to looke the Fox himſelfe in the face; to her he hieth him, with his purſe in his hand ready drawne, for looſing of time, and that as <hi>Chaucer</hi> ſaith, tied with a Leeke, that it may not be long in opening, for the houres that are ſpent in making many words, in ſuch a matter, cannot be recouered back againe. Now, deliuering his minde in this briefe manner, to one of ſo good vnderſtanding, the ſubſtance of the matter thus laid open before her: ſhe hearing the place, the mans name, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, caſts preſently all doubts behind her for Pettifoggers to take vp. Being poiſed with that balaſt, her ſhip fell to ſaile, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21420:32"/> her ſelfe turning round like a circle, with the ſtrong breath of this <hi>Argentum viuum,</hi> blowne thither and home againe, ready to breake her neck ouer the threſhold; ſhe returnes into the houſe to her peepling, ſinging, I haue her, I haue her: enough to haue caſt they youth away, enſlaming ſo his bloud with the ſuddaine fire of vnlooked for ioy But this mother Quack, with conſerues of Roſes and Barbaries, &amp; other gentle cooling ſtuffe which ſhe hath alwaies in a readineſſe for ſuch hoate liuered Gentlemen, calmed all the ſtorme and rage, proceeding from too ranck courage, euen as it were at once, bringing him back againe ſo to himſelfe with theſe <hi>probatums,</hi> that at leaſure and towards his going away, he enquired her good ſpeed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning forraine commodities.
<hi>Dun.</hi> It is maruaile ſhe would truſt him with theſe ſweet probatums till ſhe came back againe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſo ready to violate abroad. By my faith ſir, you haue ſo loſt me in mother Ducks drugs that I cannot vnderſtand your meaning. Me thinks without making any ſuch to do, he might better cheape perhaps haue ſent for her to the wine Tauerne.
<hi>Hud.</hi> Wine I confeſſe will make a conſenting anſwer that way. But is it ſo with you? will the appurtenances to theſe feuerous coniunctions, ſo prepare your bloud, that you cannot tarrie the launching till you come at your Surgeon? What man, ſuffer your pulſe to beate a little; I am almoſt at an end of this matter; then if you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſtay til you come home, beſtow your largeſſe vpon ſome one of your wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reapers that is ſtiffeſt in the back, ſhe will perhaps ſtoope the better to her ſiccle, after you haue bent her a little. <hi>Du.</hi> Surely ſir, as old as we are, I feare me we ſhal grow wild in this wood, but I long to heare the haſty ſpeed the old crampe-ſtretcher clattered ſo faſton, at her in comming to her hiue. <hi>Hu.</hi> Well ſir, the matter went thus forward with them. According to her chickens direction, ſhe found the parties ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the dore as he had leſt them. In her walke vp and downe before the ſame, ſhe had eſpied one of their ſeruants carrying in a couple of Partriges, bought for their ſupper, vpon which to looke, ſhe laid aſide the fine worke ſhe had in her ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhe might perceiue to miſlike the price: for ſuch folke wold farewell were it not for coſt. <hi>Du.</hi> All this while I find not, what might make her ſo reioyce, in ſinging; ſhe had her, ſhe had her. <pb facs="tcp:21420:33"/> 
                  <hi>Hud.</hi> With patience you ſhall heare; comforting her ſelfe with the knowledge that they loued to fare well, finding alſo the old wanton was contented his yong miſtriſſe ſhould rule him, ſo he might carrie the purſe: out of ſuch diſcoueries mother Truſſe hath bound vp theſe concluſions, that where
<hi>Bacchus</hi> cheere was, there might alſo be <hi>Venus</hi> play.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> A crafty cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets conſtruction. <hi>Hud.</hi> Then ſir, ſhe broched to her neſllecock this deuice, if he would be at the coſt to buy ſome ſorts of dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie foules, ſhe would take the paines to go to their houſe, and ſell them at an vnder value: by vſing ſo to do, ſhe was ſure to prepare her way more eaſily for her other affaires.
<hi>Dun.</hi> What another yet worſe then the deuill? <hi>Hud.</hi> To be ſhort, through this practiſe ſhe became a gueſt, and a much made on woman by them both: where ſhe ſtil waited her oportunity, to whiſper certaine lectures or points of her dangerous doctrine, in the eare of this faire flowre, whom ſhe ſaw thus prime fed at the boord, and as ſhe thought, forepined with bed reuerſions, and ſhort beneuolences, warily prying continually to diſcouer what troubled thoughts ſhe might perceiue her to ſmother vp and keepe ſecret to her ſelfe, through the feare of his frantick iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iealouſie, and her owne ignorance in remedies. Had not indeed this old leech bene at hand (as the caſe required) this flower had ſeeded away vntimely, oppreſſed with too much heate by day, and the want of nightly moiſture. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Before God, I begin to pittie the poore wench. <hi>Hud.</hi> What do you man, pittie her, and know her not? it is like if you had ſeene her as the other did, you would haue made mother Duck gone double ringed thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In faith, I am perſwaded your tale might haue bin heard, but hardly credited at theſe yeares. Yet you could not haue blamed your meſſenger, who would haue done her true intent, as well for you as for him, ſo you had waighed asheauy in her ſcales, which I know you are able to do. <hi>Dunſtable.</hi> I thinke if I ſhould meet with your Maiſterſhip in London, I ſhould go neare to put you in minde of this merriment, ſo the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man your wife were not by. <hi>Hud.</hi> You haue made your
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lfe merrie belike in conceipt, ſo that your wiſhes being ſet out al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, it is thereby like that you meane to be there before me: <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21420:33"/> and if ye be, the leaſt boy in the ſtreet can direct you to mother Duck, with whom you may louingly conferre about the truth of this matter, or the like concernings if you finde your ſelfe ſo troubled. <hi>Dun.</hi> I alwaies hinder the matter, and endanger your diſpleaſure with my troubleſome ſpeeches. <hi>Hud.</hi> Nay verily, if your meaning be no worſe then your words, there is neither danger nor diſpleaſure towards you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. <hi>Dun.</hi> I thanke you ſir, now I pray you begin again where you left, at the yong bride her diſtreſſe. <hi>Hud.</hi> Well, if I left there, there alſo ſhall begin the words of mother Bee her commiſſion, who put the yong wench in minde of her husband his age, which had bene a pleaſure to her to haue forgotten. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Nay I beſeech you ſir, hide not from me mother Ducks night ſpels, which I know are whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome charmes, eſpecially her ſelfe being fauoured by the aide &amp; conduct of that happy and ſucceſfull ſtarre, called by the Poets <hi>Dione</hi> the mother of
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus. Hud.</hi> You ſhall pardon me by your leaue, eſpecially the matter being ſuch, wherein I deſire to haue no skill. To this demaund of yours, I will aunſwer with the Dutch man, <hi>Ick kan die wijes well kunde icke die woorden,</hi> which is in Engliſh; I know her meaning, could I her phraſes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a minde ſo well prepared in the one, and ſo great skill to ſolicite in the other, you and I at theſe yeares will not doubt, but conditions were agreed of, in maner and forme, which were theſe. That the young louer for whom ſhe was agent, ſhould come in apparrell clad like a Poulter, keeping ſuch times of bringing ware, and ſuch proportionate ſorts of fowle, as ſhe was wont. Adding beſides, this caueat; that if ſhe were not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the way, he ſhould hold his birds dearly priſed to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, to the intent he might be brought to her preſence, if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions might ſo ſuffer. Beſides, it was agreed betweene them, that ſhe ſhould keepe her chamber, and faine her ſelfe ſick thoſe daies appointed for his comming, giuing charge to her people, that if the Fowler came, himſelfe with his ware to be brought vp to their Maiſter and her. Now if maiſter <hi>Oſwould</hi> were out of the way, all the better market, if not, they to take the chance that ſhould happen. To couller the matter the better withall, this mother Ducke ſued to her maiſter to be priuiledged for <pb facs="tcp:21420:34"/> her age, no more to come on theſe ſeruices, ſaying, ſhe would appoint the Mallard her ſonne, at ſuch times as he came to towne, in her ſteed to brin, his beſt and choiſeſt fowles thither, in ſort as ſhe was wont. Her maiſter, to ſaue three pence or a groate he was wont to giue her for her paines, thought it as conuenient or rather better for one to come and go, on whom there ſhould be no coſt diſpended, and ſo readily diſpenſt with mother Duck. Theſe matters thus farre in parleance, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to agreements performed and acted by this taker or countrey Powlter, holding traffick inuiolable on both ſides, to the full accompliſhment of both their deſires; till break-neck fortune, which ſuffreth nothing to be well done alwaies, threw in a ſlender chance to leeſe all at a caſt, which was wonne by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and kept by great aduenture. Her husband hauing loſt the money in his purſe abroad, at a neighbours houſe, where he was wont to play at tables, came home to fetch more money, with haſt to returne and recouer his loſſes: where he found his wife merchandizing with the Fowler, hucking and half penying to ſaue a penny in a birde, which pleaſed her husband well. He to agree and take vp this greene quarrell betweene them which were but new fallen out, as he came vp the ſtaires, caſting his eye from one to another, as they gaue him cauſe in their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, found a fault in the caſement of the Mallard his hoſe, which for haſt he could not laſe vp ſo cloſe, but that a falſe peece of a wrought waſtcoat was diſcerned to hang out. Which when the husband ſtriued better to diſcouer, the other brake violently from him leauing foule and faire and all behind him, through his good fortune of the gates being thus left open, he eſcaped their hands.
<hi>Dun.</hi> It many times commeth ſo to paſſe, that thoſe things which ſhould commend men to their loues, are leſſe ſafeties then meane and neglected things: but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it was a great chance to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, he ſhould come in, while they were thus comparing their things together.
<hi>Hud.</hi> What man how is it with you? me thinketh your lookes pleade the yong wenches caſe: ſay truly, is ſhe guilty or not guilty? and if you were her husband, what would you do in this caſe? <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Surely ſir, where nothing can be prooued, ſuſpition ſhould not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21420:34"/> part a man and his wife, might I haue perſwaded the matter. <hi>Hud.</hi> Had you bin there, you might haue done more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different ſeruice to haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp the matter, which would haue deſerued ſuch a further faucur, as women leaue not commonly vnrequited. I am partly of your mind, he came ſomwhat ſhort of his proofes, yet ſooner vp the ſtaires then he was looked for of them, who would not haue ſent for him, had he tarried vntill this time: nay perhaps ſhe had rather her husband had ran out, and the other to haue tarried. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Had it bin my caſe, for all my ſaying, I would haue made maiſter di dapper haue fline out at the roofe tiles, ſor preſuming to kanke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my neſt, vnleſſe my wife could haue perſwaded me he had bin an Funuke, and could do nothing but kiſſe her hand, or carry her Fan, and then ſurely I might ſafely haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted her to his keeping to haue looked that none ſhould come vp vnto her but his ſelfe. <hi>Hud.</hi> It is not to be doubted, but they were both too wiſe to make him priuie to their bargaine, as appeared by the one, which was not the man he diſſembled himſelfe to be. <hi>Dun.</hi> I am of this minde further, that this elegant beholder of beauties, that could be moued to loue at the firſt ſight, could alſo be put in minde to follow his occaſions buſily, according to the ſhortneſſe of the time he had with his miſtriſſe in the chamber. But euery man that breaketh his neighbors fence, treſpaſſeth not againſt his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſures. I thinke well, while they were bargaining, there might ſome beck or twinckling regarde paſſe betweene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but as for further harme, notwithſtanding the other his iealouſie, I thinke there was none. What imagine you ſir, would you credit falſe ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which hath too buſie an eye in euery corner?
<hi>Hu.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in let your conceit helpe you, eſpecially in a matter that decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it ſelfe. <hi>Du.</hi> Then I pray you ſir how ended the matter?
<hi>Hu.</hi> Surely the yong woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made her husband a peece of amends, in wiſhing him ſo yong a man as the mallard was. For the reſt that remaineth, he muſt haue patience with her, till time and place may aſſoord her the like means to make him a further amends. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> What became of the Mallard, went he home to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>Hu.</hi> He was purſued thither but not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d there. You may imagine by his haſt, he had a further flight to make: yet in her houle were found by the old ſenior, ſeathers of another couler <pb facs="tcp:21420:35"/> then he was wont to weare whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came abroad to ſel his foule. Now he comparing the ſimilitude of the man, and the ritch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the attire together, it ſeemed better vnto him to let fall his reuenge, and to whiſt the matter, then to let the world make a tale of this tranſmutation. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> How then I beſeech you came you to heare of this buſineſſe? <hi>Hud.</hi> By the common poſt that keepeth no mans counſell <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Belike he is ſome mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, you name him not. <hi>Hud.</hi> If you haue a deſire to know him, it is long winged fame, who ſitteth on euery man his houſe top, bringing with him newes of all ſorts. <hi>Dun.</hi> Now I pray you ſir, ſhew the Gentleman his name that was thus likely to be wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. <hi>Huddle.</hi> I haue not heard his name, but they ſay he hath maskt open faced with her ſince.
<hi>Dun.</hi> It was after the banquet then, elſe had it not bene
<hi>Italiano More.</hi> But I wonder how the matter ſhould be giuen out, and not the parties names with it. <hi>Hud.</hi> There are many daintie things in the world, and thoſe wholſome to, which haue no names, neither are to be found in my <hi>Lexicon. Dunſt.</hi> If they be not already in your
<hi>Lexicon</hi> they will neuer come into my Dixionarie. <hi>Hud.</hi> I am ſure I haue not lied vnto you, in ſaying there was ſuch a matter euen ſince the conqueſt alſo, yet I muſt confeſſe a long while agoe, and ſtill newes to you, becauſe you haue not heard them before.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> I beſeech you ſir haue you not taken this report out of
<hi>Chaucer</hi> his Ianuarie and his May. <hi>Hud.</hi> Indeed yes, though not in euery halfe agreeing with the ſame, the rather, becauſe I knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but maruailes would delight you. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I pray you then ſir, what became of mother Duck, had ſhe not a husband to helpe her now in her extremitie? <hi>Hud.</hi> Like enough ſhe had a Nicolaitane, who in his dayes had ſlept many an acceptable ſleepe to others, and profitable ones to himſelfe Such mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lewdsbies, are ſaid to get more ſleeping, then others can do waking. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Had ſhe no puniſhment for theſe her foule ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations? <hi>Hud.</hi> Perhaps ere this time ſhe is both catcht and skinned alſo, but for ought that I can heare, her conſtancie is ſuch, that neither for whip nor coard, ſhe will confeſſe, who the Mallard her ſonne was. Iuſtifying her ſelf beſides, that ſhe hath done nothing contrarie to her profeſſion, ſaying; euery one in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21420:35"/> their trade, may exerciſe the vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were bred &amp; brought vp in, without offence to law. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> But by your fauour ſir, ſuch foule cancellers &amp; breakers of the ſeales and obligations of marriage, cannot be too ſeuearly puniſhed. I perceiue they that make their recourſe to ſuch folkes, muſt not haue their beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnities ſhut vp in their coffers at home. <hi>Hud.</hi> No doubtleſſe, with ſuch, ſo ſoone as the dore is once ſhut, and your ſelfe gone out, you are forgotten for the gift-already beſtowed. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Me thinkes they ſhould be afeard to make any their enemies, who haue in that ſort commanded them, doubting leaſt in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger they ſhould conferre their benefit ſome other where. <hi>Hud.</hi> Nay, ſuch is their ſinceritie, that they dare giue venture to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all hazards. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I pray ye ſir ſatiſfie me in this one thing more: what do you take to be the cauſe, why ſome that vſe this vawting exerciſe grow leane, and other ſome fat? <hi>Hud.</hi> I thinke you know, or elſe can imagine the cauſe, without my telling you. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> No verely. <hi>Hud.</hi> Then I will not be dainty with you in my reaſon. They that grow fat put their whole felicitie in it, and ſo battle themſelues withall. Others, that goe not ſo hartely to it, pine themſelues away, becauſe their bodies are in one place, and their minds in another. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I neuer had thought, that in thoſe coniunctions, it had bene neceſſary to haue had two ſoules in one body. <hi>Hud.</hi> Looke euer what the louer looſeth, is to be found in his beloued. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Now your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther newes I beſeech you ſir.
<hi>Hud.</hi> There is alſo a pleaſant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port made of another Gentleman, who had an elder brother his part, of ſuch vices as were noted vnto you in the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man deceaſed, who is like enough to fit your deſire, in making away his liuing which the other kept. Beſides other his faults, he was noted with theſe two eſpeciall ones, both enemies vnto grace, <hi>viz.</hi> Pride and Ingratitude. Of ſuch notable pride he was, that the day he had not bin noted and obſerued with caps and knees as he had gone in the ſtreetes, that day he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne back againe to his chamber, taking it for ominous to haue bene ſo diſpiſed and neglected of the baſe and ignoble world, falling at defiance with his wholeſute of apparrell, the workman, and the obſcure and vnworthy people, that through <pb facs="tcp:21420:36"/> through ſlenderneſſe of their iudgements, could not value his excellencie, at whoſe begetting for ought he could coniecture, without doing himſelfe wrong, there could not be any of the gods leſſe then <hi>Iupiter</hi> himſelf. Working out the day vpon this conceipt, ſtriued with his little wit how to amend this fault, which he knew was not in the boyes of the ſtreet, whom often before he had ſeene to point at his proper perſon. Neither in himſelfe, for he rather mended his conceipt, thinking euery day better then other of himſelfe, till in the end he concluded, it muſt needs reſt in the workman and in his attire. Wherevpon his euery daies exerciſe, was to caſt and deuiſe ſtrange inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how to double and trebble coſt vpon all manner of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, till it came to ſuch expence and height, that himſelfe with his lewd deuiſors, could bring it to no greater: towards the furniſhing and maintenance of which diſguiſed outrages, great ſummes of money were waſted, to the hazard and ouerthrow of his whole eſtate of liuelihood. The good Gentlewoman his mother, hearing tell of the lewd waſte her ſonne made of his lands in this prodigall and vnworthy ſort, came home to his lodging, hoping through the intereſt ſhe had in him, together with the counſaile &amp; experience, which by report of the world ſhe might allow to be in her ſelfe, and afterwards fell out to be foo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in hir, ſhe might be bold to perſwade him, that thoſe were not the ornaments that beſt beautified a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither that his father and ancientors wan their credit and aduancement by ſuch degrees of fantaſticall and ſlouthfull ſlightneſſes, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by valiant and aduenturous deeds, acceptable and pleaſing to kings and Princes their maiſters, whom they ſerued. Which words he ſeemed not to heare, on purpoſe, to ſhew his mother in the moſt deſpitefulleſt ſot he could, her vnworthineſſe to ſpeake to him, who was neither at ſo much leaſure, nor ſo baſe minded to leeſe any time in anſwering her. Which ſhe noting, and the eaſilier by his knitting and frouncing his paire of lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly browes at her, this tender Gentlewoman, finding her ſelfe thus ouer awed by the weed her ſonne, fell into a great greefe, or freſh lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting the loſſe of the worthy Gentleman her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, this baſtard God his father, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom in the many yeares
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21420:36"/> of their liuing together, ſhe had receiued no ſuch diſcomfiture. Withall, breaking into theſe words, vttered (it ſhould ſeeme) with much griefe; Shall I die, ere I ſee the hope of one of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his vertues come from thee? Had not thy birth made thee a Gentleman, this painted apparell with thy darke conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, would prooue thee but a mock Gentleman. They that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row geſtures and apparell, to put on the out ſides of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for an houre, could they become the perſons of them they ſtriue thus to counterfait, no better then thou imitateſt thy fathers inwarde vertues, notwithſtanding their apparrell and likeneſſe of them they would preſent, they ſhould be thruſt headlong from the ſtage. Wretch that thou art, to haue one finger of thy gloue, the worſt and meaneſt thing about thee, better, and of more worth, then all thy conditions. His remembrance being thus rubbed, he gaue his mother this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie; You tell me that which I make leſſereckening of, then the lace that tieth my ſhoo. Care I for my father or your breeding me a Gentleman? or ſhould I be ſo fooliſh to thinke, the world eſteemeth or careth the more for me, in that he hath left me gentilitie, which neither he, nor you, could take from me, I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that you ſee lying before you, to whome I am more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, then to heauen or earth? Had my father left me e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of that, then perhaps his vertues you ſpeake of, might haue had my good word now he is gone. I confeſſe I haue heard my father, when he was diſpoſed to pleaſe himſelfe, to remember the ſeruices he did his Soueraignes, at Bullen, New Hauen, Saint Quintins, and I wot not where elſe beſides. Put caſe he did in theſe places, thankes worthie offices, beſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a forward and a valiant Gentleman, what is that to me? Had I no money in my purſe now to pay for my ſupper to night: thinke you the reciting or remembrance of my fathers Acts, would pay for my ordinarie? Perhaps it would, where nothing is to be had, ſo nothing and nothing, may haue a merrie meeting, but ſomething and ſomething, ſhall haue the better greeting. His penſiue mother, too much diſcontented and diſcomforted with this careleſſe and irreligious anſwer, fell into a further perturbation, or rather greeuous paſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:21420:37"/> minde, out of which theſe words were occaſioned; Alas the while, that I ſhould liue to heare a counterfait wretch, contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to nature, and borne of my body, to recken his fathers li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing too little for him, and his vertues too great. Are we come to that paſſe now, not to care how we be bred, nor on whom, ſo that lands and goods be one, let the deuill or the dung-hill be the other, it mattereth not? Had thy father carried that minde, or rightly diſcerned thy diſpoſition, he would haue left thee that which ſhould better haue fitted thy conditions, and haue beſtowed a gentle gift vpon a Gentleman. Is there a diligent choiſe made, and a principall labour taken, to make horſes fit for a Prince his ſtable, &amp; ſhall we not admit or beſtow the like care to breed and faſhion men, beſeeming a worthy Prince and nation in their better places and ſeruices? If a horſe that is not rightly bred, prooue better then the generation from whence he commeth, becauſe of the ill likelihood, it is more then was looked for. On the contrary part, if a horſe that was duly bred, miſcarry &amp; come ſhort of the likely or rather certaine grounds of well doing, it cannot be without faults in themſelues, who wanted not good breeding. Thou canſt looke for no leſſe then a heauy iudgement from God, for thus pulling downe with thy vices whom he had exalted for vertues. There I ſee money ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before thee for land I am ſure is already ſolde, &amp; I feare the reſt ſtandeth but vpon aſſurance. Lock it vp, and keepe it ſafe, ſince thy lands thou couldſt not keepe. As for thy conditions, truſt them abroad looſe I warrant thee, neither Gentleman nor honeſtman will robbe thee of them. <hi>Dunſt</hi> Surely ſir, it is a dangerous wit, which maketh a man forget nature. Had it not bene for the ordinance of nature, this Gentlemans father might haue had perhaps, more likely reaſons and better hopes to haue beſtowed his liuing vpon ſome other of his children or kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. May this geare go on this ſort, we ſhall haue an vntoward race of children, if they be no better taught then thus, to care for none, nor to ſhew duty longer, nor futher, then they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue benefits. To ſay truly: they that care not what parents they come off, I little thinke they can ſufficiently regard them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or loue their children. <hi>Hud.</hi> You did well to put me in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21420:37"/> minde of my owne forgetfulneſſe of the time of the day, which already beginneth to bid vs good night. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I wonder how a man thus puffed vp with the whirlewinde of vanitie, could keepe his bones from breaking vnder his fleſh. My Lord is not yet returned from hunting, ſo that if I haue not wearied you too much already, I may hope to enioy you yet another while, till this diſcourſe at the leaſt be at an end.
<hi>Hud.</hi> My buſineſſe being altogether with my Lord, no excuſe nor borrowed occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhall carry me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, till by the laſt ſeaſon of the euening we be conſtrained to part. <hi>Du.</hi> Then I beſeech you ſir, to finiſh theſe newes, and ſhew me what became of this Gentleman.
<hi>Hud.</hi> After all was ſold and ſpent, there fell out this merry ieſt. All his men ſauing one, were gone to ſet vp their bils in Pauls, to catch another yong maiſter, better feathered then the other, whoſe plumes they had pulled within the downe. He finding himſelfe thus forſaken, in a lunatick ſort, bad his man (thus poſt alone left with him) make ready his horſes, for he would ride home and liue ſparingly, vſing abſtinence after a ſurfet, till his halfe years rent ſhould be due. To which his man made anſwer; why ſir, whither will you go? Marry knaue (quoth he) home, &amp; named the place. To which he ſmilingly replyed; You know ſir, you tooke money for that long ago. Why villaine, quoth the Maiſter, where is the money then? I thinke Sir, ſpent, ſaith his man. The money ſpent (ſaith the Maiſter) my land ſold, and I neuer knew of it till now! In that rage, he falleth vpon his man, whom he would haue ſlaine out-right, had he not bene reſcued from him by ſome other company within the houſe.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> If he could haue coniured his land out of his man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it had bene a cudgeling well beſtowed: but I feare me there would come no ſuch duſt out of his coate. It is a pleaſant thing for a man that hath ſold his land, and ſpent the money, to dreame he hath it ſtill, till he waketh, and findeth indeed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left, but his bare deſire to haue it ſo. Yet you haue not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, what became of the Gentleman in the end. <hi>Hud.</hi> Surely it was his good hap, by lighting vpon a good mariage, with his after wit, to recompence much of his follies, purchaſing againe in the end, as much land as was left him at the firſt. <hi>Dun.</hi> Great <pb facs="tcp:21420:38"/> fortune to be twiſe a man, withall met he with any better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions then at the beginning? <hi>Hud</hi> Would you deſire better conditions then to purchaſe land? or would you wiſh him to do any thing elſe, if he were your ſonne?
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> He recompenced his mans beating I doubt me not.
<hi>Huddle.</hi> Perhaps nay, as the courſe of the world goeth now amongſt ſpoilers, the maiſter his good day, prooueth the man his ill day, and the maiſters marring, becommeth the man his making. Perhaps, when he ſold land, the other might take out of the bags that were too heauy many times with money, to make them lighter for carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. But now the world being changed, his maiſter finding no bags to hold enough, nor ſumpter horſe that will carry enough, Totnam thus become French, you may eaſily imagine the date of ſuch waſters were out, as would ſend it faſter packing, then the maiſter could get it comming. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> You haue rightly diſcribed the condition of a ſecret knaue, that were like enough indeed, beſides his priuie pilferies, to robbe his maiſter of his wits alſo, as in this Gentleman it appeared. <hi>Hud.</hi> If your ſonne would entertaine ſuch a one, it would be a good eaſe for you, which are faine to carrie his cloakebag, and walke his horſe, for want of ſuch a one. I know many ſonnes that would afford their fathers better offices: but he maketh you an amends I know, that will content any reaſonable father; for while you hold Iack nag in your hand without, he goeth in and taketh vp money after ten in the hundred, which gaineth you fortie. So I truſt you cannot ſay, but you are well paide, for bearing the budget, and walking the Palfray. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I confeſſe I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent me in ouerdooing for my towardly child, who will from time to time, and I hope at all times, deſerue it: or at the leaſt, keepe things in the ſame ſtay and order I ſhall be able to leaue him them. I like not to play the tyrant with my child, as ſome fathers do, who vnnaturally ſuck vp the bowels, &amp; deuoure the bloud of their children: who after they haue ſpoiled the fame and renowine of their anceſtors, leaue alſo behind them inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent children, on purpoſe to haue them beare the burthen of their owne outragious follies. Where the heire is thus puniſhed for the iniuſt offences of their parents, there commeth in Gods <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21420:38"/> wrath, to the third and fourth generation, by the vniuſt impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of their accurſed fathers. This is called the childs perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his fathers vowes, which he vndertooke and fulfilled not according to the charge of his firſt promiſe made vnto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God. What more godleſſe part in a manner can there be, then for wicked parents to make illegitimate their imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and lawfull children, by prodigall diſheritings? Such iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious parents, by law ſhould be forbidden to get children, who thus ſelling their liuings, leaue behind them a perpetuall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of their faults, by the teſtimony of their owne apparant wickedneſſes. What infinite euils are they ſubiect vnto, which beyond the condition of ſauage beaſts, take from their children all power and meanes, which ſhould defend and keepe them ſafe from the violence of the oppreſſor? Who after they haue deliuered ouer the honour of their anceſtours into other mens hands, leaue their owne creatures vpon a bare flint ſtone, or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courleſſe in the duſt, which no ſauage beaſt at no time hath vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily done, by her like deare and tender ones. Till ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying fathers vſurped vpon the right, wherevnto they were appointed but Baylifes of the husbandrie vpon an accompt, theſe heritages being the gift of God, remained in one ſtock and line, from generation to generation, according to the firſt vertuous bleſſing, as your ſelfe yeſterday gratiouſlie remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. Call we this beſtowing of children in our owne places, to make them heires of nothing? They that thus vnkindly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and ſet at naught their ſecond ſelfe, what delight may any other hope to finde in them? <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Me thinketh the equitie of the law, ſhould as well prouide for keeping the heritage, as to appoint the heyre.
<hi>Hud.</hi> I thinke the law makers in time paſt, thought there could be found none ſo vnnaturall, as to wrong their owne children, in ſort, as they ſuppoſed none ſo hard har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as to murther their fathers, againſt whom alſo, for the ſaid reſpect there was no law thought vpon to be made.
<hi>Dun.</hi> Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie were the children of ſuch fathers, if they might be borne againe, or their fathers new chriſtened. For they muſt needes be accurſed in their cradles, or begotten againſt their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents wils and conſents, who firſt of all, pull downe the ſeate <pb facs="tcp:21420:39"/> of their aunceſtours, then next root out the foundation of their children; after that cauſe brotherhood vtterly to perriſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay: and ſo by conſequence in the end, become a perpetuall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to the well doing of all their friends, eſpecially to tread vtterly downe, all ſuch that are in degree of proximitie in bloud with them. <hi>Hud.</hi> It ſhould ſeeme to me, that the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring of parents, is the principall cauſe to pull downe Gods heauie hand vpon them, which you haue marked and ſet out in this accurſed ſort. <hi>Du.</hi> Yea ſurely ſir, the defying of parents, argueth a waſting of Gods grace, and all manner his bleſſings. There is nothing could trouble me more, then to be wronged by a man of my owne nature, and to haue him made my fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar enemie. The man of peace whome I haue truſted and ſet out in a readineſſe, to take the firſt fruites of my labours, to be ſupplanted by him, and to ſee him gnaſh his teeth at me like a perſecuter, ô that would burie me quick! Is there a ſpite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that diſpleaſure, to haue a mans head broken with his owne foote-ſtoole? I muſt needs call for my graue to defend me, when my neereſt and deareſt neighbour ſhall approach me with violence, and ſtand vp ſtiflie againſt me. When I ſhall finde that I tooke for ſuppled honie, to become ſtiffe darts, what ſhall I then do? Are they not words ſofter then honey, for the child to craue the father his bleſſing vpon his knees? And are they not darts infected with deadly poiſon, for the Sonne out of the ſame mouth to ſay, I reioyce in this day, wherein I haue preuailed againſt my father? Nay, are not theſe the words of a meere Sathaniſt, out of his hart to ſay; Death take my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hold him faſt, I haue deliuered him fettered and bound in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy hands, thou ſhalt murther him with little ſtriuing, for I haue taken reſiſtance away from him? How like you ſir of theſe dutifull recompences, to reward a tender father withall? could you not be contented to ſee ſuch an heire faire hanged, and that in time too, ere he had deminiſhed that whereto he had no right, to make rome for a more worthy to come into his place? <hi>Hud.</hi> Is this that you would haue your ſonne to ſtay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon in ſuch order and ſort, you ſhall be able to leaue him in. Are you from a kinde father, become the tragicall tyrant you
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21420:39"/> ſpake of euen now? or haue you made a triall of your ſelfe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time may come to play that part in earneſt, you haue hither to dallied withall? Thankes be to God, your caſe hath bene ſuch, to finde alwaies a leaſure, to looke vpon lamentable ſpectacles in others a far off, &amp; haue at no time bin conſtrained to come vpon the ſtage, to play a part your ſelfe. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Could I play any part to do you ſeruice, according to the intendment of my heart, I would willingly without conſtraint, performe my ſeruice, in what ſoeuer ſort it may pleaſe you to command my poore abilitie. Would God your worſhip had remooued diſpleaſures, and taken vp ſtrifes, while they were new begun, before they had altered to that vehement ſharpeneſſe, and bene aggrauated to that greatneſſe, which ſince hath brought a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aduerſitie and vexation vpon you, the rigour wherof hath conſtrained you to indure ſuch vnkindneſſes, as the world in the like caſes affoordeth. <hi>Hud.</hi> I ſtand in very little neede I thanke you, to haue theſe vnpleaſantneſſes renued or made laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto me; but rather am compelled, by the crueltie of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe worſe then a
<hi>Dyſenteria,</hi> to vſe the remedie of a medicine againſt the deuill his biting called patience. <hi>Dun.</hi> To be plaine with you ſir; If you ſell the Lordſhip of the towne wherein I dwell; forſaking all other parts, I will play the <hi>Caonian</hi> Doue, and be gone ere the Hawke come.
<hi>Hud.</hi> Your are a ſhrewd Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon to pull, come it once to billing, it had need be a hardie hawke that ſhould bring you vnder her beake. If you ſcape the ſowfe you will it, and legge it, too too ſwift for a ſhort winged Hawke one the plaines, and too ſtrongly for along winged Hawke in the couertures, or buſhie coppiſes. I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more harme by three kinds of baſe birds, that haue their blouds bruſed within them, which I will be content to name vnto you then by all the Hawkes you can recken that haue any ſparke of naturall goodneſſe in them. The birds names be theſe Rookes, Stock-doues, and Starelings. But of the three, the leaſt harme I haue receiued from the Starelings, and the rather becauſe my owne commiſeration hath cauſed me to beare with them The other two, for theſe noiſome properties eſpecially, I am troubled with. The one is, they are full of hurt, the other <pb facs="tcp:21420:40"/> that they are profitable to none. The Rookes, looke whome they take an vnkindneſſe againſt, as it is their beaſtly natures and properties indeed, to be noiſome &amp; troubleſome to all ſorts of birds, looke I ſay what they cannot maiſter ſingle and of an euen hand, they bring in a rage and tribe of helpers, to the downfalling of them they haue conceiued ſhrewdneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt. The Stockdoue in like ſort, when he hath laid an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in your way, for which he looketh for your indignation and diſpleaſure, if you but ſtalke at him as they ſay, without fire in the cock, ſtraight his taile goeth higher then his head, giuing you a proud obeiſance or malepart courteſie, which you muſt take for a full recompence of all your harmes. I ſaw this other day in a wood of my owne, one of theſe rancke blouded Stockdoues, breaſt a pheſant from his perche, as diſdainfully as if himſelfe had bene Lord of the wood alone. The Pheſant you know how harmeleſſe and generous a birde he is, hurting none, neither ſtriuing at all, but when he is compelled to reſiſt. <hi>Dun.</hi> I meruaile ſurely how the Doue could miſlike that beautifull and louely birde. <hi>Hud</hi> I can eaſily take away your wonder; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Pheſant had better bloud in his body, then the other lowring and wrie looking wretch. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> To continue my ſpeaches to you, to whom I meane as to my ſelfe, I wiſh you to hold faſt, and make much of ſomwhat while you haue it, leaſt hereafter you ſeeke that you had, and could not keepe where it will not be found. I am but a poore thinne Kettle, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would be loath to be knocked againſt a thick braſſe pot, whoſe ſmiting would ſurely prooue my breaking. I loue not to take wrong and to be threatned alſo. I had rather be pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing while my bones be whole, then to be promiſed golden ſplents when they are broken. I like not thoſe priuie mocks, to be made bare of my goods, and then to be pitied: the ſhame that is ſo put vpon me in my extremity, is far worſe then indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate neceſſitie it ſelfe. It is a wayfairing mans propertie to make much of the pot, and neuer to let it go out of his hand when he is drie, till he haue ſupped it of cleane: then when he hath left it licquorleſſe in a rage, to caſt it againſt the ground. I like not while I haue ought, to be ſtroked and ſcorned together with <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21420:40"/> theſe faire words, what wants thou, let me know and I will helpe thee. They that be brought downe through ſuch ſimple confidence ſhall be raiſed againe at leaſure, committing all to fortune, like as when a man hath fooliſhly ouerſeene his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game which was furthered by good caſting, thinking to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſame with the muſe of his wit, playing an after game at Iriſh. God bleſſe me from ſuch mercileſſe minded men, as can ſo lead a man into a foole his paradiſe, and there leaue him ſuccourleſſe. When I am tempted by any ſuch ones buſie que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions or dangerous communication, it is my beſt and ſafeſt way, to be alwaies found in a dreame. Were I a riche man, I might ſpeake prowd words, and haue them iuſtified at the full, but ſince I am but poore, I will ſpeake ſuch words as without offence may take place.
<hi>Hud.</hi> Sithence the black mantle of the night, hath foulded vp within her darkneſſe this daies light, I am alſo contented to let the firie light of this exerciſe die in my hand, bearing patiently the burthen of the heauie ſaddle you haue faſtened vpon my ſilly Aſſelike back.
<hi>Dunſt.</hi> Nay rather I beſeech you I being Gods ſilly creature, commonly called a packhorſe, ſuffer me to carry the laſt ſacke to the mill. Since the multiplying of ſpeeches to this large proceeding, haue growne out of my deſire, to haue faſhions and patterns reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their wonted guiſe which you haue maintained and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, to ſtand already in a better frame: wherefore now, ſhew I beſeech you, the right abuſe your ſelf haue obſerued in matters worthy reproofe and amendment. <hi>Hud.</hi> If it be my rule, you deſire to haue things ſquared by, I had rather keepe a Feruler to admoniſh them which corrupt the language and capacitie they haue freely giuen them to exerciſe, then at all to finde fault with ſuch, who ſhew to haue more wit in their hands, then the other haue in their heads. It is the new faſhion ſpeach that troubleth me. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> I beſeech you ſir, ſhew the abuſe therof, for I am perſwaded the ſingularitie or meruellous fineneſſe therein troubleth the whole world. <hi>Hud.</hi> I am conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſhew you their cripledneſſe that I haue obſerued to hault in that kinde. Some ſpeake, as if they had a mint going in their mouthes, &amp; lack a ſtampe to figure their words. Others ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:21420:41"/> as though they were matching their words, as Fletchers do Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row heads to their ſhafts Others ſpeake, as though their words were hidebound in their mouthes, and lack a maſh of liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and Reaſons of the Sunne, to looſe their toungs. Others keepe their mouthes ſhut vp a long while, to make their words ſtrong and forcible, on purpoſe to ſhoote birdboults. Others haue ſuch a ſharpe looſe, in letting go of their words that they are able to make you an anſwer, before they know your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund. Others ſpeake ſo ſcornefully, as though they bought their words by whole-ſale, and were too good to retaile them againe. Other ſome ſpeake their words ſo thick, that you muſt tarry the chewing them, ere you can conceiue what they ſay. Others ſpeake with ſuch a grace of morall ſentences and phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that you would thinke that they eate no other meat but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothegs and Dixionaries. Others keepe a ſchoole of manners in their mouth, euery word giuing back, to haue the other goe before. Others are as daintie of their words, as if they bought them by Haberdepois, and would keepe them till a deere yeare, that they might vtter them by Troy or grand waight. Others ſpeake ſuch brackiſh and pickled words, that they are faine to lay them a watering in the foame of their mouthes, ere they can vtter them. Others ſpeake ſuch high and loſtie words, that they are faine to ſet open the broad gates of their mouthes, for the wicket is too little for their larded words to come out at. Others ſpeake, as if there were more vowels then conſonants. Others ſpeake ſo ſhort, as if their words were made of the medicine that cureth the toothach. Others ſpeake, as if their words were made all of one liuerie, &amp; were afeard of the ſtate of retainers, ſuch men haue likely the Iaundies, or ill affected liuers, as may appeare by the duskie coulour in their faces. Others ſpeake as though they were ſacrificing their words, and quartered them with their teeth, as they come out of their mouthes: thoſe be ſuch, as their words be euer better then their deeds. Others ſpeake their words ſo graue and ſo ſad, that you can diſcerne nothing by them but their coullour, which is for the moſt part Lion tawnie, into ſuch you muſt digge deepe to know their meaning. Others haue ſuch bouncing words, ſent ſo ſtrongly <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21420:41"/> from their lungs, that they that are ſubiect to the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, had not need to ſtand in their way. Others ſpeake ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily, as though their words were made of <hi>S. Helens</hi> beades: ſuch tell their words as they vtter them: you muſt take heed of thoſe, for they are euer bored through the middeſt with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie. Others ſpeake, as if they had eaten all their meate at the mill dore, and had ſcraped their words out of Mault duſt: ſuch when they ſhold ſpeake, fall a cackling. Other ſome ſpeake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked words, as if they ſhot them out of a Croſſe-bow: it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous for a tame beaſt to meete with ſuch. Some ſpeake as leaſurely, as if they tarried for a winde, to bring their words from <hi>Franckford</hi> mart, where if the exchange prooue good, you ſhall be ſure of a banquet of conceited words. Other ſome ſpeake as if their words were made of wilde Hops: ſuch mens tongues runne alwaies poaſting before, and their wits come halting after; ſuch a wit had <hi>William Sommers.</hi> Others ſpeake ſuch ſpangled words, that you would thinke they had them all at the Imbrotherers: ſuch commonly neuer ſpare for any coſt. Others ſpeake ſuch odoriferous prouocatiue words, that you would imagine them to be made of Amber grieſe: when ſuch open their mouthes, all the coaſt is perfumed, as it was when
<hi>Cleopatra</hi> breathed vppon wanton <hi>Anthony.</hi> Others tell a tale, as if they were making a Bridge of words betweene Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth marſhe and Greenewitch parke. Others ſpeake as blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſlie and Giant-like, as they did at the confuſion of toungs in Babilon, who had bene better the doores of their mouthes had bene dammed and ſhut vp, then to haue propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the deitie with ſuch ideot-like words, as were neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with meditation, framed with counſell, nor directed ſo much as with a heathen iudgement. <hi>Dunſt.</hi> Had I not croſſed my ſelfe, and remooued out of your circle, I had bene a dead man ere this. <hi>Huddle.</hi> Why man, ſhew me the bugge, that we may runne away both together.
<hi>Dunſtable.</hi> Your worde odoriferous, hath made euery ioint of me to tremble and ſhake, and my haire to ſtare and ſtand vpright on my head as you ſee. <hi>Hud.</hi> How may a man keepe off a ghaſtly ſpirit, with croſſing <pb facs="tcp:21420:42"/> himſelfe, or otherwiſe profit himſelfe, by that ceremonie of croſſing, ſhew me that skill for a parting blow.
<hi>Dunst.</hi> The vertue thereof I know not, but my owne cuſtome that I can teach you. When I meete with a ſtrange or contrarious thing vnto me, the like whereof I haue neither ſeene nor heard off be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. I ſtraight take it for ominous, and to prognoſticate ill luck vnto me, which to preuent, that it creepe not vpon me, I ſtand vpright, making the ſigne of the croſſe on my ſore-head, to ſtand me in ſtead of a Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to couer and defend my whole bodie.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:21420:42"/>
            <head>The Argument of this booke, according to the Authors meaning.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I promiſed in my epiſtle to the Readers, to put no interdations or diſtributions of my owne ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, betweene the authors words and meanings, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to enlarge or diminiſh their ſpeeches, yet becauſe there are no partition walles ſet vp and laid, betweene one ſpeech and another, through out their whole diſcourſe, I haue thought good, hoping it may be done without offence, with ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of mine owne rough hewing, to deuide the floores of the roomes within this worke, for the further benefit, if it might be, of the well diſpoſed readers. If I come ſhort or miſtake any thing herein, for lack of knowledge, being not made priuie to the deuiſers conceits, I deſire as at the beginning, it may be pardoned of the wiſe and indifferent reader, the rather, becauſe I haue not taken vpon me to ride aloft be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the authors meanings, but altogether go about, humbly to reſound vnto the world, the eccho which was beaten back vpon me from out the wood or Parke wherein theſe matters were talked of. Againe, though thorow the whole booke there are few words that go for nought, yet dare I not venture to expound them accordingly, as I might barely imagine them to be ſpoken, leaſt I ſhould make my ſelfe thereby a coactor or gatherer vp of other mens meanings, as if I were able to beat out the braines of their ſufficiences, whoſe expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and knowledge, I muſt of neceſſitie giue place vnto. That which I am able to performe, I offer my ſelfe willingly vnto, which is, to lay open ſuch doubts as may ariſe to ſuch as are not readily diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of themſelues, to labour or regard the true intent and meaning of the dialogers; who in my conceit, were altogether deſirous to benefit if they could, ſuch Gentlemen as dayly ſeeke to murther themſelues by all maner degrees of violent follies. Vnleſſe in time they better reſpect themſelues, neither this ſupplying plaiſter, nor Maiſter Kellie his great Elixer will be able to reſtore or recouer them from out their <pb facs="tcp:21420:43"/> daungerous conſumptions, who by diſorderly gouernment, make this incurable diſeaſe alſo hereditable to their children, ſo that the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne medicine it ſelf can giue the no remedie, vnleſſe in time they ſlie the priuie ſnares, which all ſorts of enimies both ſleeping and waking intend againſt them. As the ſpider with poiſoned twiſt vnſeene, begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the ſilly flies, ſo with the deadly ſting of theſe venimous deceiuers, thorow too much outragious follie, do Gentlemen fuffer their bloud, and their childrens bloud, to be ſucked vp. The first ſpeaker within this dialogue, is called an ancient retired Gentleman, becauſe of his lowlie and milde kinde of liuing, not at all diſpoſed to ſtriue with the world, in a proud buſie reſtleſſe ſort: the other is termed a midling or franckling. The world acknowledgeth no ſuch degree, as they of that ſort deſire to be holden in, which is to be accounted more then a yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and leſſe then a Gentleman: ſuch ones are ſaid to harrow hell, to make their ſonnes Gentlemen. Wherevpon commeth this by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word, Maiſter how call you him, the ſonne of goodman what ſhall I call him. Theſe kinde of men are inſtant wonderers at lewdriches, which when the canckered and malicious minded wretches enioy in any plenty, then ſtraight they thinke, the troth and grace of all things, conſiſts in themſelues, preſuming that their children and themſelues put on new natures, by attiring them beyond their birth and degree. This ſort of men
<hi>Palingenius</hi> tooke great diſpleaſure at, ſaying; If riches and worldly droſſe ſhould make Gentlemen, then the Butcher, the franckling, the Barbar, the Fiſhmonger, the Sheapheard, the Tanner, the Bawde, the theefe, the Vſurer, and all of euery filthie ſort, whom the vnequall hand of Fortune hath exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, might cloute out their gentilitie. But God and nature forbids ſuch as proceed from thoſe baſe conditions, addicting their mindes wholy vnto that which can deſerue no worthy laude nor praiſe, to attaine the gift and force deuine of gentility, which is onely atchieued thorough vertuouſneſſe. Good enterpriſes and vertuous deeds, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto this degree, and not the body ſet out with gorgeous ſhews: ſo that the minde alone procureth gentilitie, which is an ornament to none, but to him that doth appropriate himſelfe to vertue. Many of meane degree haue bodies and outward ſhapes bred in them tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the force of nature, which for all that, ſtill retaine in minde a baſe conceit of vertues. Neither God nor nature giues this value <pb facs="tcp:21420:43"/> vnto all; but deales onely bountifull herein with ſuch, as reſpectively incline themſelues to better their conditions. If gentilitie conſiſted in triumphing names and brags of riches, what lack might not be then a Gentleman? To ſhe ſtouthfulneſſe, to haunt righteouſneſſe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the diſtreſſed, to prouide for the weake, to defend the iniured, by theſe meanes was gentilitie at the first attained. All men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in equalitie, till vertue made the difference. Then were not men admitted to principall and greatest offices, that could gaine or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe most. Then was not authoritie fenced in with wickedneſſe. It must needs be a miſerable common-wealth, where the best officer ſhall become the worst author and maintainer of naughtineſſe. It is a wofull authoritie that defendeth wickedneſſe. Offices were not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for ſuch as could moſt politicklie enrich themſelues, but rather for thoſe which were likelieſt to performe vnto their Prince and common-wealth best ſeruices. If nothing ſhould be law, but the decree and pleaſure of them that ſit in the commaunding place, vvhat hope ſhould any haue long to enioy it, in that certaintie and orderly frame, that gratious and wiſe Princes haue commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them? Princes lawes therefore, are not to be executed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the pleaſure and commaundement of their officers, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to the office and dutie, in conſcience and honeſty from their prince they are charged by. Gracious Princes thinke it not ſufficient for themſelues, to be conuerſant and exerciſed in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, vnleſſe alſo they hold their principall offices in the ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their iust and expedient lawes. If it be fit for the Prince himſelfe to be dect with iudiciall effects, outward pompe and oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatious ſhowes will not alone ſuffice to diſcharge inferiours duties in their offices. Such as from an high place offend in their office, no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count or correction can be ſo ſtraightly taken, as the qualitie of their offence meriteth, faulting against the taske impoſed vpon them by their Prince, for the whole common-wealths good. Such in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, were by their principall leader or chiefe worthie, clearlie diſfranchiſed from the ſocietie or conuerſation of men. The ſtrict exerciſes of iuſtice in the magiſtracie, cauſed the Romaine Empire ſo long, and ſo not ably to flouriſh. But when they fell at their owne luſt, to diſpence with lawes, ſhaking off moderation and abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, then ceaſed their happineſſe, and after them followed a more <pb facs="tcp:21420:44"/> vnthrifty ſeed, which made an viter end of all proſperous yeares, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vertue in the end vtterly adue, making the noble birth of their aunceſtours, through the ſtaine of their villanies, a reproach vnto them, ſhaming them alſo to whome they ſhould haue paſſed their bloud by teſtament of vertues. As the body engendreth a body where nature is complete, ſo doth the minde beget a perfect minde, according to ſuch perfections of vertues, as were entire in the ſtate of vertues in the antecedent &amp; noble worthy. By ignorant times in this place, is ment the ſort &amp; ſtate men liued in, ere they were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the deſire of knowledge, before there was any ſearch made into naturall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the generall vſe of creatures. Becauſe there ſhould no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention ariſe who that principall worthy was, that mended thus the condition of men, he nameth him not. At no hand he will allow him, that hath an eye to himſelfe, without reſpecting the good of others, how riche or great ſo euer he be in the world, to be a conſtant man, firme in vertues, but only a proud puffin of the world, or a Pippin of S. Ioanes wood. By hypocrites, in this place are ment, ſuch as hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelues beyond cauſe towards ſome, on purpoſe to lift them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vp beyond reaſon, againſt other ſome. Such are ſaid to imitate the outward habite and ſhape of vertues, but neuer to put on the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward abilitie of well doing. Such hipocrites, in their ſlattering pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes reſemble the deuil who offered our ſauiour Chriſt all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world, to the intent to take from him (if he would haue bene tempted by him) the incomparable riches he was already poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of. The ſeditious Ieſuites, are here called poiſoned Serpents, and hooded Friars, becauſe they haue put on the hoods of Rome and Spaine, which are murther and rebellion, ſent hither by the Pope and the King of Spaine, who are called greater Serperts then themſelues. Friars haue alwaies bin cariers and recariers of the traſh of Rome, ſo as theſe leſuits are now. By calling his dames houſe a chappell of eaſe, is meant, his ſextrie or veſtry, wherin he was wont to beſtow his holy relicks, called by the frankling the Friars demiſaries and by the Apothecaries
<hi>Teſticulum canis.</hi> By fortunes wanton, is meant ſuch a one, whoſe luſt goeth ouer all things without being ſatisfied: ſuch a one as is euer ſick of the ſurfet of plentie. Fortitude is called a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant vertue, becauſe the couragious hart thruſteth out the bloud from the ſhroud of the fearfull breaſt, to ſuccour and ſtrengthen the <pb facs="tcp:21420:44"/> vaines and outward parts of the body, which are in a more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to execute valorous things. By the hockie dame, is meant <hi>Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> the goddeſſe of harueſt, to whom husbandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue thanks, &amp; pray for reſt and quietneſſe after their great and ſore labours. Digeſtion, is called, a conſtant and a ſubſtantiall-humor, medled in the body by oppoſite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mixtions, the better part wherof in the end by outward &amp; inward heat is aduanced to bloud in the body, wherby life is fed and maintained. Ingratitude, eſpecially towards parents, the enemie to all graces. Voluptuous pleaſures, gnaw in ſunder the ſinowes of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. By the <hi>equinoxium</hi> is here ment a ſimilitude, betweene a reſtleſſe woman and the Aſſe, which is ſaid in that ſeaſon eſpecially to bray twelue times in the day, and twelue times in the night. By the Phiſition his foure times comming, is meant thus much: Firſt he comes to heare his patients confeſſion, how he diſordered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at the diſeaſes entrance, whereby to finde the nature therof, and ſtate of the ſick mans body: the ſecond time, to miniſter Phiſicke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diſeaſed his griefe: the third time, to launch into his diſeaſe by auſtereneſſe of phiſick, to open the windowes betweene life and death: the fourth time if he chaunce to come, it is to pronounce ſentence of death. By the diuers conſtructions of his diſeaſe, amongst his men, there is meant to be ſhowed, the properties of the ignorant, for they euer take vpon them ſtill diuerſlie, and for the most part, euery one contrary to another in opinion. Becauſe he hated to do well, he was therfore ſaid to be in a frenzie, and to refuſe the light Drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and voluptuous perſons are alſo ſaid to be in a lethargie, or deadly ſickneſſe, and ſo to ſtand in need of the aire, and the light thereof. He was ſaid to haue a deadpalſey all ouer his body, becauſe it is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of the ſinewes, weakning the ſtrength and most effectuall parts of operation in a mans body wholy and at once, ſurpriſing life and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo that death cannot be reſisted in ſuch a one. <hi>Caonia</hi> is a part of
<hi>Epirus,</hi> a region in Greece, wherein is a wood called Dodoni, haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a multitude of Stockdoues, wherevpon this prouer became, <hi>Caoniae columbae,</hi> craftie Pigeons of <hi>Caonia,</hi> becauſe the yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great preparation of ſhips which the Greekes made, theſe birdes fore ſeeing the downfall of the wood, fled into another country. This craftie Franck ling likewiſe, dwelling by a harmleſſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, from whom, without doing any deſart, he was ſure to receiue <pb facs="tcp:21420:45"/> benefit, was content to giue him check mate. But when one was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to poſſeſſe the foreſaid Gentlemans ſeate, which was like more ſtraightly to looke into this churle his vnworthineſſe, him he calleth a Hawke, whoſe comming he may not abide to here tell off. Of all birdes this Doue is ſaid to be most priuie to the nature of a hawke, and to liue in most contempt of hawkes. Couetous men, in this place, are called the diuels Faulkners, becauſe it is the propertie of them, when they are ſeazed of their pray, and gotten into their tallents more then they can well gripe, or need to gorge themſelues vpon, yet in that while, if there come any other pray by, which is like to be within their maiſterie and command, they force the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues at that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which ſheweth their cormorant deſire to be ſnatching. Beſides, from the height of their ſtand, they are able to make many ſlights, and ſuch as by their ſwift and fast flying, are neither ſeene nor heard, till they be ſeized of that they purſue. The Pheaſant here, his bloud is praiſed, becauſe it is medicinable and effectuall to many good purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. By the Stockdoues breaſting, to driue the Pheaſant from her ſtand or pearke, I take it is meant lack Straw, Wat Tiler, and the rest of his fellow rebels in Richard the ſeconds dayes, who by their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick and rude billing at the Pheaſant, would haue put back the best blouded birde within this wood, from his high pearch, had they not bene preuented by the vertuous endeuour of ſuch an excellent wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, as for his vertuous act at that time ſhewed, hath enriched many others ſince, to a degree of worthineſſe, and that for his vertues ſake. <hi>Dione</hi> is the mother of <hi>Venus,</hi> to whom chits and bawds are ſaid to pray vnto, to ripen their young plants, and to make them ſlack, pliant, and ready for their harueſt: and that their young heiffors may grow to vſe for the yoake and the paile, ſooner if it were poſſible, then nature requireth. The other ſtarre here meant, is called
<hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferum, Venus</hi> her owne ſtarre, to whom bawdes are wont to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, when they were deceiued or robbed of any of their ſequestred weanlings: deſiring by her light, that they may be reſtored to the knowledge vvhere they are: beſeeching alſo hir aide to be reuenged of thoſe wrongs, in as much as ſhe hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them into her protection, to whom they are ſworne by othe neuer to forſake that profeſſion. By an Eunuke here, is meant an officer to keepe good rule in Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens chambers, or elſe ſuch a one altogether, which the bawde hath <pb facs="tcp:21420:45"/> in charge, to keepe <hi>Cupids</hi> tender ſacrifices inuiolated. The Bawds houſe is called a Hiue, in reſpect that as in a Hiue all Bees are ſo like one another, that they cannot be diſcerned: ſo within this hiue of good fellowſhip, there is to be found ſuch a ſwarme of perfect ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, that you cannot diſcerne who is the worſt. The riotor or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiat body, here is called a <hi>Didopper,</hi> becauſe the kinde of this birde delights in many changes of puddles and vncleane vvaters. The bitterneſſe of theſe dialoguers diſpleaſures, is eſpeciallie exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt thoſe, that by exceſſiue riote and wantonneſſe, pull downe the renowne of their anceſtours, decaying thereby themſelues and their children, greatly ſhaming beſides, to ſee water-bearers, and ſuch as haue done most meane and deſpiſed ſeruices vnto them, to become better worth, and more able to liue then theſe vngratious kinde of conſumers.
<hi>Eneas</hi> was not called a godly and an happy man, becauſe he carried away vvith him from the deſtruction of Troy ſixteene diſſents of Grandfathers, that neuer foiled the reputations of their first anceſtors, but rather chieflie, in that through his labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and painfull vertues, he was able to reſtore his decaied houſe to former happineſſe, being ſo bleſt of God, that before he died he ſaw a large propagation of his owne progenie and naturall bloud, to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh againe by his induſtrious labours. To the Gentlewomans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of breeding horſes, I haue thought good to adde <hi>Virgils</hi> words, concerning the excelencie of their firſt nature. A horſe ſaith he, from his firſt foaling, that is duly bred, lifteth vp himſelfe with ſuch ſteps, gate and pace, as willeuer after prooue proper vnto him. And at the firſt he is of boldneſſe to venture and to paſſe ouer hard and vnknowne things, fierce then alſo to go against dangers, as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, hedges, ditches, and ſuch like. Beſides, to be ſo inſtant and hoate in courage, that he feares no ſudden or tumultuous noiſe, as armour, ſhot, or outcries of men. Shewing further by his breath, eares, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts about him, ſuch animoſitie, that ſomtime with his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious high neighing, he ſeemes to fill the places round about him, and to deuide the aire neere vnto him. Afterwards, with ſuch bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe you ſhall ſee him inſult vpon an enemie in the field, vnder his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that you would imagine through the force of his generoſitie, he had a deſire to pull the Launce or Curtelax from out the enemies <pb facs="tcp:21420:46"/> hand. If there be ſuch worthy things peculiar and proper to beaſts in their firſt natures, let no man doubt, but there is a more deuine and effectuall force by the ſecret and miſticall prouiſion of nature, properly to diſcend from one worthy man to another. Where he ſaith, happie vvere the children of ſuch deſtroying fathers, if they might be borne againe, I take it, he meanes their happineſſe, which by new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be adopted, to make good their firſt birth-right, whereof they were fraudulently deceiued. By that he vvould have their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers new chriſtened againe, it is not meant by vvater of a new foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, but rather as I take it, by the mercie of God to be redeemed from that curſe, vvhich ſome children are ſaid to haue giuen them in their cradles. Where he ſaith, there wanted vnitie betweene their parents, at their conception, it is not meant that they were not gotten without concirtation, or the lifting vp of both their conſents: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they were begotten against the grace of God, as thoſe are that proceed from forced mariages, where wanted agreement of hearts, which is called a falſe and an vnchriſtian coniunction of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Where the father is ſaid to carrie his ſonnes cloak-bag, is meant ſuch a man, as hauing gotten a reputation amongſt his neighbours, to be holden and reputed honest, with the credit thereof is contented to colour and excuſe to his power, his ſonnes lewdneſſes. It is good for the world in time, to ſee to the fraudulent entents of ſuch, which carrie their ſonnes cloake bagges: and alſo warely to looke to ſuch prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks, as put their fathers in their pockets at their pleaſures. When ſuch yong maiſters begin to gentle it, ſtrifes, diſcentions, and lawe ſutes, are made rife and comberſome in the world. Then haue Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and the well diſpoſed of all ſorts, great cauſe to looke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and to hold theſe Boarepigs and Beare whelpes at the ſtaues end, who for all their ſlickt coates and ſmooth tongues, vnderſtand not what courteous behauiour and gentle deeds meane. They that thinke to carrie candels before theſe young deuils, are in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be ſtifled with their ſtinking ſnuffes. The moderate Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that haue to do with theſe hoydens, ſhalbe ſure to reape in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe, what they ſowe in curteſie. By the <hi>Panacea</hi> or ſuppling plaiſter in this place, is meant forewarning rules for them, who know not how to guide themſelues, and haue made themſelues weake tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough <pb facs="tcp:21420:46"/> babiſh pucillanimitie, that they might yet with an after-wit, ſtrengthen themſelues with that which remaines, if they haue not already made a bloudy defect, and ſlaughtered themſelues with that weapon that was left them by their worthy aunceſtors, to defend themſelues. To thoſe that haue not ſet themſelues beſides the eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, let this teach them not to admit ſtrange maiſters and commers into their fathers houſes and heritages: and that becauſe Kites can be no goodkeepers of Chickens. Likewiſe, for thoſe that haue med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led too farre already, vnleſſe there be but one way with them, and that they be paſt remedie to be redeemed: let I ſay, this caueat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them, that it is ſurer ſtanding vpon fleſh legges, then vpon woodden ſtiltes, and that it is ſurer holding with both the hands then with one. Let them further beware, that their liuings prouided by their friends, prooue not <hi>Tantalus</hi> his orchards, by which is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, that there are good things comming towards men, if for want of grace they do not preuent it themſelues. The whole intent of theſe two carefull fathers ſpeeches, within this dialogue, hath bene to teach all ſorts of men, eſpecially Gentlemen, to beware of ſelfe-vvill and ſelfe loue, preſcribing remedies withall, how to keepe men from aſpiring, and coueting greater things, then their likelyhoods can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme: ſhewing alſo in eſpeciall, how inward vertues are the meanes to aduaunce and ſet men vp in approoued degrees of worthineſſe, and not baſe riches, ieſtures, apparell, nor hypocriticall policie, vvhich of all the reſt ſtaines them most, vvho in place of iuſtice, with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe practiſe nothing elſe. By loue-tales and other ordinarie matters within this booke, is ment no more but this, to ſhew into how manifold dangerous precipitations (by playing rex with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues) Gentlemen in this age are fallen into. As by too gaudie and too gorgeous apparell; then vvith voluptous and exceſſe diet; then beſides, with too outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and vvanton luxurie, vvhereby they vnnaturally deſtroy, first their bodies, then vngratiouſlie looſe their ſoules, and last of all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſlie, and too too vnkindly, deface the name and fame of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, their anceſtors, and whole poſteritie. Now to conclude, I craue pardon at this time, in that I haue not taken the paines to deuide or diſtribute into ſeuerall parts, this diuerſe diſcourſe, neither ſo much as vvith marginall notes, lead the authors meaning in ſome words. <pb facs="tcp:21420:47"/> The principall cauſe vvhy I haue omitted ſo to do, is becauſe I had no purpoſe from the beginning, to vvrong the ſpeakers meanings. Therefore, looke vvhat errors I haue added of my ſelfe, I haue thought good to let them take their owne places by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, hoping, ſuch as come gentlie minded to the reading hereof, vvill allow me ſome liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and pardon for a vvhile, till vvith better leiſure, I may be able more fitly to ſatiſfie them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Richard Field. 1594.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21420:47"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
